<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epulario, or The Italian banquet wherein is shewed the maner how to dresse and prepare all kind of flesh, foules or fishes. As also how to make sauces, tartes, pies, &amp;c. After the maner of all countries. With an addition of many other profitable and necessary things. Translated out of Italian into English.</title>
            <title>Epulario. English</title>
            <author>Rosselli, Giovanne de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841253</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00309)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 539:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epulario, or The Italian banquet wherein is shewed the maner how to dresse and prepare all kind of flesh, foules or fishes. As also how to make sauces, tartes, pies, &amp;c. After the maner of all countries. With an addition of many other profitable and necessary things. Translated out of Italian into English.</title>
                  <title>Epulario. English</title>
                  <author>Rosselli, Giovanne de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[dam] I[slip] for William Barley, and are to bee sold at his shop in Gratious street, neere Leaden-hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Opera nova chiamata Epulario.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]¹ B-L⁴ (-L4).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Italian banquet.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cookery, Italian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5822:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5822:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Epulario,</hi> Or, The Italian Banquet: Wherein is ſhewed the maner how to dreſſe and prepare all kind of Fleſh, Foules or Fiſhes.</p>
            <p>As alſo how to make Sauces, Tartes, Pies, &amp;c. After the maner of all Countries.</p>
            <p>With an addition of many other profitable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Italian into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by A.I. for William Barley, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Gratious ſtreet, neere Leaden-hall. 1598.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5822:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5822:2"/>
            <head>The Banquet, called in Italian, <hi>Epula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio:</hi> wherein is handled the manner of dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all kindes of meates, birds, and all ſort of fiſhes. <hi>Alſo ſhewing how to make Sauces, Pies, Tarts, &amp;c. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vſe of all nations.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>The firſt booke, ſhewing what meat is beſt roſted, and what beſt boiled.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fleſh of Beefe is beſt boiled, and of Veale the breſt is good ſodden, the loine roſted, and the legs made in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues. All parts of the ſheepe are good boiled, only the ſhoulder, which is beſt roſted, as alſo the legge. Porke is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together wholſome being freſh, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chine is good roſted, the reſt is ſalted as you thinke good. Kid is all good to be roſted or boiled as you thinke good, but the hinder quarter is better roſted, the like of Lambe. Goats fleſh is good from the Month of Ianuary with ſauce made of Garlike. The ſide of a Bucke is good in Bacon broth. The Loine may be roſted, and the legs baked, the like may be done with a yong Kid. Wild Bore ſhould be peppered and larded. The Hare is good roſted, but the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part is better boild. Connies are better roſted then any other way, and the beſt part of them is the hinder legs.</p>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:3"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe Capon, Peacocke, Feiſant, and other foule.</head>
                  <p>Shoueler, Puet, Ducke, Crane, wild Gooſe, Heron and Storke, are all good and would be ſtuffed with Garlike, oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or ſuch like things. Peacocke, Feiſant, Partriſh, wild Henne, Quailes, Thruſh, blacke Bird, and all other good Birds are to be roſted. Pigeons are good both roſted and ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, yet beſt roſted. Ring-doues and wild Pigeons are good roſted, but better boiled with Pepper, Sage, Parſely, and Margerum. Capon is good both boiled and roſted, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Henne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſeeth all kind of fleſh that it may ſhew faire.</head>
                  <p>You hauing cut it in as many péeces &amp; parts as you thinke good, then lay it to ſoke in faire water for the ſpace of an hour, which done waſh it againe in freſh water, and then with hot water, then ſet it ouer the fire in the Kettell or pot wherein it may haue roome inough, that it may be the whiter: then put as much ſalt to it as ſhall be néedful, and be careful to ſkim it: if your ſalt be not cleane, put it in whot water, and let it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein till it bee melted, and conuerted into water or pickle, which being ſettled, you may put into the pot or Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of meat, alwaies taking care not to put in the dregs of the pickle, becauſe it is foule. But if your fleſh be old &amp; tough eſpecially Capon or Hen, then ſhift them out of the boyling water, and put them into freſh water, and ſo they wil be fair, and ſooner boiled.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make all kind of meat to roſt faire and white.</head>
                  <p>To make all kind of foule, Capons, Kid, or any other fleſh to roſt faire and white, ſpecially Béefe, Mutton, Veale, or Lambe. Firſt parboile it, and then larde it, if it be Capon, fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,
<pb facs="tcp:5822:3"/>
or any other foule: firſt waſh it cleane, that done, dip it in hote water, but take it preſently out againe and lay it in cold water, and it will be the fairer and roſt better: then lard it and ſticke it with cloues or other things as you think good, or as he that oweth it doth moſt fancy it: if you will you may ſtuffe them with ſwéet hearbes, dry proines, ſoure grapes, cherries, and ſuch like things, and ſo ſpit it, and firſt make a ſoft fire that it may roſt ſokingly &amp; not bee ſcorched or burnt, and when you think it almoſt roſted, grate white bread, and caſt ſalt into it, wherewith you ſhall crumme it, then make a hot fire, and turne it round, ſo it wil be fair and white, which done, ſend it preſently to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a good deuiſed meat, or ſauce.</head>
                  <p>To make good deuiſed meat of Goat, Hare, wild Boare, or any other wild beaſt. Take of clarret wine and water, of ech a like quantity, and waſh the fleſh in them, then ſtraine that water and wine through a cloth, putting therto as much ſalt as is requiſite, which done, boile the fleſh therein, &amp; when it is boiled, take it out; and if you deſire to make two diſhes of it, take a pound and a halfe of Currans, and bruſe them well with as much bread, which you ſhall cut in péeces, toſt, grate, and being in crums, ſoke in good vineger, which done, beat the Currans and the bread together: and if you can get of the blood or entrailes of the wild beaſt, it will be very good to mixe with them, which being well beaten together, it muſt bee tempered with baſtard wine, that is wine ſod with new wine, called Muſt, and with the vineger wherwith the bread was ſoked, let it paſſe through a ſtrainer into a pipkin, wherein you ſhall put cloues and Sinamon, as much as you think good, and as it is neceſſary, and make it ſtrong or ſwéet of vineger &amp; ſpice, according to the maner, or as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> owner will haue it. Then let it boile halfe an houre vpon a chafingdiſh, with a ſoft fire, on the one ſide then vpon the other turning it often with a ſpoone: then fry the fleſh with good lard and cut
<pb facs="tcp:5822:4"/>
it in péeces, and lay it in diſhes, and couer it with this deuiſed meat, and the blacker it ſheweth, the fairer it is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make broth of the fleſh of wild beaſts.</head>
                  <p>Firſt waſh the fleſh well with good white wine mingled with as much water, and ſtraine the waſhing, and ſéeth the fleſh therin, putting to it a good quantity of lard cut in ſquare peeces as great as dice: which done, put thereto a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of ſage, being pulled in three or foure péeces with your hands, and when it is almoſt ready, put ſpice into it, as I ſaid before. And to make the broth ſomewhat thicke, take two or thrée yolkes of egges, according to the quantity thereof, and as much bread well toſted at the fire, but not ouermuch, only to drie it, which you ſhall make into ſmall crummes, then take a little of the broth, and ſtrain the bread and egges into the pot of broth: and if thou canſt get ſome of the blood or the entrailes of the beaſt, you ſhall beat it well and ſeeth it with the ſame broth, &amp; it will be the better. But if thou wilt make any diſhes of this broth, the fleſh is to be cut in péeces of halfe a pound or of a pound: and if you will make pottage, it muſt be cut very ſmall: you muſt alſo reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that the fleſh wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this meat is made of, or elſe broth, muſt be boiled in the water wherein it was waſhed, becauſe you may not looſe that blood which commeth out of it in the waſhing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce for Veneſon.</head>
                  <p>To make ſauce for veneſon, firſt boile the fleſh in a quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of water mingled with as much vineger, &amp; when it is boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led take thy fleſh out of the broth, that it may ſhrinke and dry: and being dried, frie it in good lard: and if you deſire to make two diſhes thereof, take a pound of Almonds vnpilled, and beat them together with the meat, then take a pound of bread cut in peeces, and toſt it at the fire, but not much. Which done, lay it to ſteepe in a little red wine, and beeing
<pb facs="tcp:5822:4"/>
ſteeped, beat it together with the foreſaid thinges, then tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it with the broth of the ſaid fleſh, and ſtraine it into a pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, and ſet it on a ſoft fire, to boile for the ſpace of halfe an houre. Then put therein ſome Pepper and Sinamon, that it may haue the ordinary taſt, or that it may be ſtrong or ſweet as the maiſter of the houſe will haue it. Then take an onion and ſeeth it with larde cut in ſmall péeces, and when the ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſodden, ſtampe it and mixe it with the larde wherewith it was ſodden, and put them into the pipkin with the other things aforeſaid, and let them boile together, then diſh the meat and lay this ſauce vpon it, and ſend it to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſmall paſties of Veneſon or Goats fleſh.</head>
                  <p>To make Paſties of Veneſon or Goats fleſh, firſt cut the fleſh into diuers péeces as big as your fiſt, then par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boile them in water, vineger, and ſalt, as much as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, then take it forth and dry it, which done, larde it, firſt rouling the péeces of cut lard, &amp; this fleſh in pepper and Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with ſome ſalt all beaten together, then take cloues and ſticke them on all ſides of thy peeces of meat, then take good floure and make the cruſt thicker then a pancake, and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry peece of fleſh you ſhall make a ſmal paſty, then bake them ſokingly and well, and theſe paſties may bee kept fifteene daies or a month.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make pies of Veale, Capon, or any other fleſh.</head>
                  <p>To make Pies of Veale, Capon, Birds, or any other fleſh. Take as much of the leaneſt part thereof as you thinke good, and mince it ſmall, then take the ſuet or fat of a Calfe, and mixe it with the meat, and ſpice it according vnto the common manner, that done, make your paſſe as you did for the paſties, and bake them in an ouen. And when they are
<pb facs="tcp:5822:5"/>
baked, take the yolks of two Egges, Vergiuice, a little Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and mixe them with butter and water, which poure into the Pies. And if you cannot make the cruſt, then boile the meat ſo dreſt as aforeſaid in a pan like a Whitepot, in ſuch Pies you may put one or two Hennes, Capons, Pigeons, or any other foules either whole or minced.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Pie in a poſſenet or pipkin.</head>
                  <p>To make a Pie in a pipkin, Firſt take the fleſh and good Béefe ſuet, and mince it ſmal, and put it in a pipkin, and if you wil, you may put therein Capon, Henne, or Pigeon, then ſet it on the coales, and when it beginneth to boile, ſkim it. Then take a few ſmall Reaſons and an Onion, and mince them ſmall, and fry them with good ſuet, and put them ſuet and all into the pipkin, and when it is ready, put ſpice and vergiuice into it. And if thou thinke good put therein likewiſe yolkes of two or three egges beaten, which done, you may diſh it and ſend it to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Pies of the Combes of Cockes and Hennes, with their ſtones, and liuers.</head>
                  <p>Cut ech combe in thrée péeces, and the liuers in foure, but leaue the ſtones whole, then take a little larde, and cut it ſmall, but beat it not, and take thrée or foure egges with béefe ſuet well beaten, and it will be better with the marrow of an oxe. Then take thirty or forty cherries although they be dry, Sinamon, Ginger, and a good quantity of Sugar, and ſome cloues, mingle them together, and thereof make a Pie, which done, bake it in an ouen or a frying pan, and being halfe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, take the yolk of an Egge, Saffron, and Vergiuice, and beat them together, and put them into the Pie. And ſo let it bake, then ſend it to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:5"/>
                  <head>To make fiſh Pies.</head>
                  <p>Take the fiſh and waſh it cleane, and cut it with ſlaſhes on both ſides, then take Pepper and ſalt and caſt it into the cuts, and alſo into the belly of the fiſh, then make the paſt ſomewhat thicke, and putting the fiſh into it, ſow vp the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereof, which done, let it bake ſokingly in the ouen till it be throughly baked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Pies that the Birds may be aliue in them, and flie out when it is cut vp.</head>
                  <p>Make the coffin of a great Pie or paſty, in the bottome whereof make a hole as big as your fiſt, or bigger if you will, let the ſides of the coffin bee ſomewhat higher then ordinary Pies, which done, put it full of flower and bake it, and being baked, open the hole in the bottome, and take out the flower. Then hauing a Pie of the bigneſſe of the hole in the bottome of the coffin aforeſaid, you ſhal put it into the coffin, withall put into the ſaid coffin round about the aforeſaid Pie as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſmall liue birds as the empty coffin will hold, beſides the Pie aforeſaid. And this is to be done at ſuch time as you ſend the Pie to the table, and ſet before the gueſts: where vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or cutting vp the lid of the great Pie, all the Birds will flie out, which is to delight and pleaſure ſhew to the company. And becauſe they ſhall not bee altogether mocked, you ſhall cut open the ſmall Pie, and in this ſort you may make many others, the like you may do with a Tart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make the cruſt of Pie or Tart of Pigeons, Pullets, or Kid.</head>
                  <p>To make the cruſt of Pigeons, Pullets, or Kid fleſh. Firſt boile your meat a little till it be almoſt inough, then cut it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſmall peeces, and fry it in good ſuet. Then in a pan make
<pb facs="tcp:5822:6"/>
a cruſt of thicke paſt like a Pie cruſt, and put the meat in it, couering it with dry Pruines or Cherries, then take Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gice with a little whote water and butter, and tenne Egges with parſely and Margerum, and beat them altogether with a knife, and then put them in an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rthen pot, and ſet it vpon a fire of coales, ſtirring it alwaies with a ſpoone. Then poure this broth vpon the cruſt, and ſet it on the fire, as if it were a Tart, and when you thinke it to bee baked, ſend it to the Table, and make the cruſt ſweet or ſharpe as your mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter fancieth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a double fried meat of any fleſh, Pigeons or Pullets.</head>
                  <p>Firſt take thy meat and make it very cleane, then cut it in quarters or in ſmall peeces, and put it into a pan and frie it with ſweet ſuet, ſtirring it with a ſpoone, and when it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt boiled, take out the greateſt part of the ſuet, then take Vergice, three or foure yolkes of egges, a little broth, and good ſpice, and put them into the meat, and let it boile vntill it be almoſt ready. Then take a little parſely ſhred or beaten ſmall and put it in a platter, and ſend it to the Table, ſwéet or ſharpe according to your maiſters deſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Miraus of Spaine.</head>
                  <p>Firſt take Pigeons, Pullets, or Capons, and dreſſe them as if they were to be roſted, and ſo ſpit them, and when they are halfe roſted, take them off the ſpit, cut them in peeces, which done, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into an earthen pot. Then take almonds ſcorched on whote embers, and wipe them cleane, &amp; without more wiping of them ſtampe them in a morter: then take to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted bread with three or foure yolks of egges, and ſtamp them with the almonds, and temper them with a little vineger and broth ſtrained through a cloth, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put them into the pipkin with the meat, and ſet them on the coales with good
<pb facs="tcp:5822:6"/>
ſtore of ſpice, eſpecially Sinamon and Saffron, and Sugar ynough, and let it boile for the ſpace of an houre, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ring it with a ſpoone, and when it is boyled, ſend it to the table in a flat diſh or platter, or els in pottage which is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Peacocke with all his feathers.</head>
                  <p>To dreſſe a Peacocke with all his feathers, in ſuch ſort that when it is ynough it ſhall ſéeme to bee aliue and caſt fire out of the mouth. You muſt kill the Peacocke with a feather or quill pricked into her head, or els make her bléed vnder the throat like a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, then cleane the ſkin vnder the breaſt, that is from the neck vnto the taile, and flea it off, and being flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed turne the ſkin of the necke outward néere to his head, and cut the necke, ſo that his head be faſt to the ſkin, and likewiſe let his legges hang to the ſkin, then ſtuffe it full of ſome dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pudding, with ſpices, and take whole cloues, and ſtick them in his breaſt, and ſo ſpit him and roſt him by a ſoft fire, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke wrap a wet cloth, that the fire may not drie it ouermuch, ſtill wetting the cloth: and when it is roſted, take it off the ſpit, and put it into the ſkinne, then you muſt haue a certaine yron cunningly made faſt to a trencher, which ſhall goe through the Peacockes féet and not bee ſéene, that ſo the Peacocke may ſtand vpon his féet, with his head vpright, as though hee were aliue, and dreſſe his taile in ſuch manner, that it may be round. If you will haue the Peacocke caſt fire at the mouth, take an ounce of Camphora wrapped about with Cotton, and put it in the Peacockes bill with a little Aquanity, or very ſtrong wine, and when you will ſend it to the table, ſet fire to the Cotton, and hee will caſt fire a good while after. And to make the greater ſhew, when the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke is roſted, you may gild it with leafe gold, and put the ſkin vpon the ſaid gold, which may be ſpiced very ſwéet. The like may be done with a Feiſant, or any other birds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:7"/>
                  <head>To roſt a Kid with Garlike.</head>
                  <p>Take the Kid and larde it with Garlike very well, and ſtuffe it full of cornes of Garlike well pilled, then take Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice, the yolkes of two Egges, and two cornes of Garlike well beaten in a Morter, with a little Pepper, and ſome fat broth, mixe them all together, and ſet it vnder the Kid while it roſteth, and baſt it therewith, and when it is roſted, put it in a diſh with that ſauce: the Kid would bee well roſted, and eaten whote.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt a Kid otherwiſe without Garlike.</head>
                  <p>Take the Kid and larde it well, then take the Liuer and lights and beat them well together with ſuet, that done, take ſeuen or eight Egges ſodden, and beat them with Parſely, Mint, and a little Sage, and mingle them together, putting thereto Pepper, Saffron, and a few cloues, wherewith you ſhall ſtuffe the Kid, and ſo lay it to the fire, and let it roſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingly, baſting it oft with the foreſaid ſauce, without garlike.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt a Pig.</head>
                  <p>Firſt let him be ſcalded white and cleane, then cut him in the belly and take out the guts and entrailes, and waſh it cleane, then ſhred Garlike very ſmall with larde, grated Chéeſe, Egges, Pepper, and a little Saffron, mixe them togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and put them into the Pig, then ſow it vp and ſpit it, but let him coſt ſokingly, &amp; let him be well roſted both outwardly and inwardly, then make a little liquor with vineger, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and two branches of Roſemary or Sage, and baſt the Pig therewith. The like may be done with Géeſe, Duckes, Crane, Capon, Pullet, and other Birds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:7"/>
                  <head>To roſt a Pullet.</head>
                  <p>When thou haſt roſted him well, take the iuice of an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe, or elſe Vergice, with Roſewater, Suger, and Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and lay the Pullet in a diſh with this ſauce, and ſend it to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt ſmall birds.</head>
                  <p>Take the Birds and waſh them well, not taking out the guts, then take Vine leaues, and put them in Salt, Fennell, and a little lard, and lap the Birds with that mixture in thoſe vine leaues, and ſet them to roſt (halfe an houre or leſſe, for they are ſoone roſted) vnder whote embers. If you will roſt them on a ſpit, tie them foure and foure by the legges and the backes together, that the breaſts may not be bruſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt Thruſhes and make ſauce for them.</head>
                  <p>Roſt the Thruſhes as the manner is, then take fair white Almonds well beaten in a morter, therto put Saunders, that the ſauce may bee red, temper them with a little Veriuice, and ſome broth, with good ſtore of Ginger and Sinamon, then ſtraine it into a pipkin, and let it boile about a quarter of an houre, and when it is boiled and put in a diſh with the Thruſhes. You may make another kind of ſauce with iuice of Orenges and Lemmons, Salt, and other ſwéet Spices.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt Partridges after the Caſtilian manner.</head>
                  <p>Take the Partridges and roſt them, and when they are roſted, take them from the ſpit, and cut off the winges, and all the meat of the breſt, and body of the Partridge, which peeces
<pb facs="tcp:5822:8"/>
lay in ſalt with a little ſwéet ſpice &amp; Cloues mixed together with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuice of Orenges, Lemmons, or Vergice. Which muſt bee done when the Partridges are whote.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Oliues of Veale or other fleſh.</head>
                  <p>To make Oliues of Veale or any other fleſh that is lean, take the legge and cut it in long thin péeces, and beate it well vpon a table with the flat ſide of a knife, then take Salt, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, and Coriander ſéed, and lay them vpon the ſlices or pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of fleſh, then take Parſely, Margerum and lard, and bruſe them together with ſome ſpice, and ſtraw it vpon the péeces of fleſh, then roule them vp together and preſſe them for the ſpace of an houre, which done, ſpit them and roſt them, not ſuffering them to dry ouermuch.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Collopes of Veale.</head>
                  <p>Take the leane of a legge of Veale, and cut it in ſmall pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and beat it with the flat ſide of the knife, then take Salt, and Fennell, or Coriander ſéede, and ſtraw it on the meat, and if time will ſerue, preſſe it for the ſpace of halfe an houre, then broile them vpon a gredyron, turning it often, baſting it with Butter or ſwéet Suet to kéepe it moiſt: you muſt not broile them dry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Liuerings of Veale or any other yong fleſh.</head>
                  <p>Take the leaneſt of the legge, and mince it with a little larde and the fat of Veale like Pie meat, then take Parſely and Margerum minced ſmall together with the yolke of an egge, and a little grated cheeſe, according to the quantity you will make, with Spice and Saffron, &amp; mingle all theſe things together with the fleſh: then take the Kell of a Hog, Shéepe,
<pb facs="tcp:5822:8"/>
or other beaſt, ſo it be good, and bind theſe things in the Kell, making euery peece as big as an egge, then roſt them on the ſpit with a ſoft fire, and not ouermuch.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a new diſh called Tomaſcella.</head>
                  <p>Take the Liuer of a Hogge or other beaſt, and boile them a little, then grate them as you doe chéeſe, and ſake the panch of a Hogge according to the quantity of the Liuer, and beat it well, then take a little new fatty chéeſe, Margerum. Parſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Currans, Spice, and Egges, and beat all their together with the Liuers, then make them in round b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the bignes of a Walnut or an Egge, and bind or wrape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ima péece of the Hogs maw or panch, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fry them in a trying pan with ſwéet butter or ſuet, but not too dry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Puddings of Hogges or Calues fleſh.</head>
                  <p>Take leane fleſh without ſinnewes of the leg, and Hogs ſuet, with the fat of Veale, and mince them as ſmall as you can, then take old Chéeſe, and a little new Chéeſe, Spice, Egges, and Salt as much as is requiſite, mingle them well together with ſome Saffron, then take Hogs guts as many as you will, and make them very cleane, that there bée no fat nor filth in them, and fil them with this mixture, which done, tie them vp and make them long or ſhort as you thinke good, they are vſed to bee ſodden, but they will not laſt good aboue two daies. Yet as time and neceſſity requireth, they may bee kept fiftéene daies or more, if they be wel vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make good Sauſſeges.</head>
                  <p>To make good Sauſſeges of Pork or other fleſh, take both of the leaue and fat together without ſinnew, and mince it very ſmall, if you haue ten pound of fleſh, put thereto a pound
<pb facs="tcp:5822:9"/>
of Salt, two ounces of Fennell ſéed, and two ounces of Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per groſſe beaten, and mingle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together, and ſo let it ſtand the ſpace of one day, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take guts well waſhed &amp; made clean, and fill them with the meat, then dry them in the ſmoke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Calues or Oxe head.</head>
                  <p>Take the head and ſcald it with whote water like a Pig, and make it very cleane, then ſéeth it, and for ſauce take gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and if you will roſt it, you muſt bake it in an ouen like a Pigge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To fry a Calues or Hogs braine.</head>
                  <p>Take the braines and waſh them very well, then caſt out the water, and breake the braines well, then take Egs, Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per beaten, and a little Salt, and mixe them with the braine, and ſo fry it with a little Suet or Butter: and when it begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to conieale together, put it into a diſh, and caſt ſpice vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: and this would be eaten preſently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Pudding in a Calues maw.</head>
                  <p>Take the maw and make a hole in the ſide thereof, and fill it with a mixture made of old Chéeſe, Egges, a little Saffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Currans, Parſely, Margerum, and Mint, wel beaten and mingled together, and being in the maw ſow it vp, and ſéeth it very well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To know if a Gammon of Bacon be good.</head>
                  <p>If you wil know when a Gammon is good, thruſt a knife in the middeſt of it, and if the knife being pulled out ſmelleth, it is good: if to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary, it is not good. And if you will haue it to kéep long, take White wine or Vineger, and as much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but better without water, and therein boile the gammon of Bacon till it be halfe ſod, then take it off the fire, and ſet it
<pb facs="tcp:5822:9"/>
ſoke in the liquor till it be cold, then take it out, and in this manner it willbe good, and continue long.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth Tongues.</head>
                  <p>They would not be ouerfat, but red, and ſod like the Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of bacon, but the tongue, the fatter it is the better it wil be, and ſhould be better ſod then the Gammon of Bacon, and all ſalt meat would be boiled in this ſort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a broth for a boiled Pullet.</head>
                  <p>To make broth of Grapes for a boiled Pullet, the Pullet would be boiled with a little ſalt fleſh, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is halfe boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, take ſoure grapes and cut them in the middeſt, and take the kernels out of them, and boile them, and when they are boiled, take Parſely, Mint, Pepper &amp; Saffron, beaten &amp; min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced together, and put them in the diſh with the Pullet and the broth and ſend it to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a new diſh after the manner of Rome.</head>
                  <p>Cut your meat in péeces as big as an egge, then take a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſalt, and Fennell, or Coriander ſéed, which you ſhal ſtraw vpon the ſaid péeces of meat, which done, preſſe them a little and put them on a ſpit to roſt, and betwéene euery péece ſpit a thinne péece of larde to kéepe the meat moiſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt or ſeeth a Pigeon without bones.</head>
                  <p>Dreſſe your Pigeons well, and make them very cleane, then let them lie in ſtrong Vineger for the ſpace of foure and twenty houres, which done, waſh them very well, and roſt or boile them as you thinke good, and ſtuffe them full of ſpice and other things, and by this means you ſhal find them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bones.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:5822:10"/>
               <head>The ſecond Booke: Teaching to make all kind of meats, and firſt to make a white meat of the fleſh of Capons or Kids, of twelue ſorts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake two pounds of almonds, and blanch them very white, and that they may be the whiter, let them ſtand a day and a night in freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then ſtampe them very well, and when they are ſtamped, put a little water to them, that they be not oile, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the fleſh of the breſt of a Capon and ſtampe it with the Almonds, and take crummes of a white loafe, and ſoke it in the Capon broth, and beat it with the aforeſaid things, then take a little Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice, halfe an ounce of Ginger, and halfe a pound of Suger, and temper them altogether with the Capon broth, &amp; ſtraine it through a cloth into a pipkin, and ſet it on the embers, far from the fire, ſtill ſtirring it with a ſpoone, and let it boile for the ſpace of halfe an hour and when it is boiled put to it three ounces of Roſewater, then make your meſſes, or couer the fleſh of the Capon or other bird therewith, and ſend it to the table: and for the better grace or ſhew, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſend it to the table, ſtraw it ful of the kernels of a Pomgranet. And if you will haue this meat of two colours, take the yolke of an egge and a little Saffron, and mingle them together with a part of the meat, and make it ſomewhat ſharper of Veriuice, then the reſt of the meate that is feaſt white, and in that ſort it is called brome flowers: and if you haue two Capons couer the one with the white, and the other with yellow.</p>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:10"/>
                  <head>To make twelue kinds of white meat after the Catalonian manner.</head>
                  <p>Take a pot ful of Goats milk, and eight ounces of flower of fine Rice, and boile it in the milke, then take the fleſh of the breaſt of a Capon new killed, and let him be halfe boiled, then pull it in ſmall péeces as big as threds, and put it into a morter to beat, but giue it but two ſtampes, and when the milke hath boiled halfe an hour, put the ſaid Capons fleſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it with a pound of Sugar, and let them boile for the ſpace of halfe an houre or there abouts, and ſtirre it well as long as it ſtandeth on the fire: and to know when this is boyled, take out thy ſpoone and it will ſéeme freſh, then put Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it as aforeſaid, and diſh it, ſtrawing Sugar vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo ſend them to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make white meats after the manner of Catalonia.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound and a halfe of Almonds well blanched and ſtamped, which being tempered with the broth of a Pullet and ſtrained, ſet them to boile in an earthen pipkin, then put into it two ounces of Rice floure firſt tempered with the Almond milke, which you ſhall boile for the ſpace of halfe an houre, ſtirring it with a ſpoone, then put to it a pound and a halfe of Sugar, and a little of the fleſh of a Capons breaſt wel beaten, which Capons fleſh ſhould be ſodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the almond milke as ſoon as it is ſet ſet vpon the fire, and when this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is well ſodden, you ſhall adde thereto a little roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſh it, and ſtrawing a little fine ſugar vpon it, ſend it to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth Rice in fleſh or Capons broth.</head>
                  <p>To make ten diſhes of brothes, take a pound of Almonds
<pb facs="tcp:5822:11"/>
well blanched, and a pound of rice, which you ſhal waſh twiſe or thriſe in warm water, then ſet it on the fire in boiling wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and let it ſéeth, and being boiled, let it ſtand in the water that it may ſwell, then ſtampe the Almonds, wetting them with freſh water, becauſe they ſhall not bee oily, tempering them with Capons or other broth, then ſtrain them, &amp; ſet the milke to ſéeth in an earthen pipkin, putting therto a pound of Sugar, and when they begin to boile put the Rice into them, and ſet them in a pipkin vpon the coales, not to néer the fire, ſtirring it with a ſpoone that it ſmell not of the ſmoke. In like manner you may ſéeth Rice in Goats milke or in other milk: and note that ſuch kinde of brothes doe eaſily ſmell of the ſmoke: Which if it happen, the remedy, firſt to take the broth out of the pipkin, but looke you touch not the bottome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and put it in another clean pipkin, then take a péece of lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth folded in thrée or foure folds, and wet it in freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then wring out the water and lay the ſaid péece of linnen ſo doubled vpon the pipkin of broth, and let it ſtand ſo for a quarter of an houre, then wet the cloth againe, and put it on if néed be, and by this meanes the ſauour of the ſmoke wil be taken away: I neuer found a better way then this to take it away, and it is very good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make broth of leane fleſh.</head>
                  <p>Take the leane fleſh of a Calfe ſodden in water and ſalt, beat it well and let it boile in fat broth, putting vnto it crums of Whitebread, and a little Pepper and Saffaron, and let it boile halfe an houre, then let it coole a little, that done, take Egges, grated Chéeſe, Perſely, Margerum, Mints, well ſtamped together with a little Veriuice, then beat them all together with the foreſaid fleſh, and ſtirre them with a ſpoon: this kind of broth would bee thicke, and in this manner you make liuerings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:11"/>
                  <head>To make a kind meat of guts.</head>
                  <p>The Guts would be well waſhed and made very cleane, and then ſodden with a bone of Bacon, to giue them a good taſt, and without ſalt becauſe they may be the whiter, when they are boiled cut them into ſmal péeces, and mixe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Parſely, Mint, Sage, ſalt and Pepper, then again giue them a boyling, and ſo diſh them, and ſtraw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a little Chéeſe or ſpice which you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of wheat ſodden with broth of fleſh, Capon, Hate, or Pigeons.</head>
                  <p>Firſt take a pound and a halfe of Wheat &amp; waſh it clean, then ſéeth it in broth of Capon, fat Pullet, or other good fleſh, and let it boile wel, ſtirring it with a ſpoone, and when it is ſodden put to it Pepper and yolkes of Egges, and mingle them together, you muſt make it yellow with Saffron.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of Turneps.</head>
                  <p>Make the Turneps cleane and cut them in péeces, then ſéeth them in fat fleſh broth, that done, ſtamp them and ſtrain them, and ſo let them ſéeth againe in fat broth, with a little Béefe or Bacon, with Pepper and Saffron.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make broth of a Gourd.</head>
                  <p>Make them cleane as they ought to bée, then ſéeth them in fleſh broth, or elſe with water alone, adding thereto certaine Onions as you thinke good, and when it is boiled take it out, then either bruſe it ſmall or ſtampe it, and ſtraine it through a Cullander, and then againe ſet it to ſéeth in a pipkin with fat broth, and a little Veriuice, and let them bee ſomewhat yellow with Saffron, and when they are ſod take them off
<pb facs="tcp:5822:12"/>
the fire, and ſet them to coole, then take yolkes of Egges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quantity, and beat them with a little old chéeſe, and put them to the ſaid meat, ſtirring it with a ſpoone leaſt it ſmell of the ſmoke, then diſh it and caſt ſpice vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make yellow broth.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound and a half of Almonds vnblanched, &amp; ſtamp them well, then take the fleſh of the breaſt of a Capon, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther birds roſted or ſodden whether you wil, with the yolk of Egges, beat them all with the ſaid Almonds, adding vnto them a pound of Sugar, Sinamon, Ginger, and a little Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and temper them with the broth of a Pullet, or other fat broth, and a little Veriuice, and ſtraine them and ſet them to boile on the coales with a ſoft fire, that they ſmell not of the ſmoke, and ſtirre it with a ſpoone, and let it boile for the ſpare of halfe an houre, and when it is halfe boiled, put into it thrée or foure ounces of good ſwéet Butter, and ſo ſerue it, with caſting ſpice vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a kind of Leach.</head>
                  <p>Take the yolkes of foure egges, halfe an ounce of Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, foure ounces of Sugar, two ounces of Roſewater, and foure ounces of the iuice of Orenges, beate all theſe thinges together, and boile them and make it ſomewhat yellow, this is common in ſummer time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a kind of made meat in fleſh time.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of old chéeſe, and a little new chéeſe, and a pound of the belly or panch of a fat Hog, or a Cowes Vdder ſod, then take good hearbes well beaten, Pepper, Cloues, and Ginger, adding thereto the fleſh of the breaſt of a Capon wel beaten, and all theſe thinges being well tempered and mixed together, then make good paſt, and lap all this in the paſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:5822:12"/>
make them no bigger then halfe a Cheſtnut, then fry them in Capons greaſe or other fat broth, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yellow with Saffron, let them not boile aboue the ſpace of thrée Pater noſters, then diſh them, and ſtraw them ouer with grated Chéeſe, mixed with other ſpices. The like may bee made of Feiſants, Partridges, and other Foule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a paſt or meat of floure.</head>
                  <p>Temper thy paſt as aforeſaid, and break it into diuers pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then ſet it to dry in the ſun, &amp; it will continue two or thrée yeare: when you will ſéeth it, it muſt be ſodden in fleſh broth or broth of a fat Hen for the ſpace of an houre. But if it be not fleſh time, ſéeth them in almond milke or Goats milke with Sugar, and becauſe this milke will not boile as much as this paſt requireth, boile them firſt in clean water as Rice is boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: your paſt alſo ſhould be baked. Theſe paſt meates would likewiſe be yellow with Saffron, except when they are boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in milke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of young Beanes with fleſh or otherwiſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Beanes and blanch them with whot water like al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, then ſet them to boile, and when they are boiled, put to them a little Parſely, and Mints well beaten, and ſeeth them with ſalt Béefe or Bacon, let it be ſomewhat gréen and it is the better. The like may be done with peaſe and other fruits when they are gréene.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To fry peaſe with Bacon.</head>
                  <p>Take the Peaſe cod and all as they are &amp; boyle them, and take a little Bacon larded with fat, and cut it into Collopes, then fry it a little with the aforeſaid peaſe, adding thereto a little Veriuice, Sugar, or ſirope of Mulberies, and a little
<pb facs="tcp:5822:13"/>
Sinamon. In this ſort alſo are white peaſe fried.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of Melts with broth of Pullets or other fleſh.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the melt with fleſh broth, let it boile ſoftly, ſtirring it, and let it not ſmell of the ſmoke, and make it yellow with Saffron, but it would firſt be well waſhed with whote water like Riſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a certaine kind of meat of Capers with fleſh.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound and a halfe of Caper, and boile them vntill they begin to open, then take a pound and a halfe of blanched Almonds well beaten, and put them to the ſaid Capers, beat them well againe with the crums of a white loafe, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them with the broth of ſome good meat, then ſtraine it and ſet it to boile vpon a ſoft fire, ſtirring it with a ſpoon, then put into it a pound of Sugar, halfe an ounce of Ginger, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and Roſewater with good ſpice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of floure, and how it is ſodden or dreſſed.</head>
                  <p>The floure is to bee boiled in good Caponbroth or other fleſh, and it muſt bee put into the broth by little and by little, ſtirring it alwaies with a ſpoone, and boile it the ſpace of half an houre vpon the coales with a ſoft fire, that it ſmell not of the ſmoke, then diſh it and caſt chéeſe and ſpice vpon it. In Lent boile it in Almond milke, Sugar, and Roſewater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of grated bread.</head>
                  <p>Boile the grated bread in good broth, then take grated chéeſe and beat it with Egges, and the bread being boiled, let
<pb facs="tcp:5822:13"/>
it coole, then put the ſaid Egges and chéeſe in the bread, and mingle it well together, and make it yellow with ſaffron.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a meat of yong Roſes.</head>
                  <p>Boile them in broth, and when they are almoſt ſodden, put to them a little Parſely and Mint ſmall ſhred, and if the broth be ouerthinne, ſtraine it with a few crummes of bread, and when it is ſodden put ſpice vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of Parſely.</head>
                  <p>Take Parſely rootes, and pull out the ſtring or pith which is within them, and make them very cleane, and boile them very well in fleſh broth with Pepper and ſaffaron, this may likewiſe be done with oile.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of Fennell.</head>
                  <p>The Fennell is ſod like Coleworts, but it would bee cut ſmaller and ſhorter, with a little Pepper, Bacon, or oile.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of Quinces.</head>
                  <p>Séeth thy Quinces in broth of leane fleſh, then ſtampe them and temper them with Almond milk, made with broth of Pullets or fleſh, and if time ſerue ſtraine them, and put them into a pipkin with ſugar, ginger, ſinamon, and a little ſaffron, &amp; ſet them to boile on a ſoft fire, becauſe it ſhould not ſmell of the ſmoke, and ſtirre them with a ſpoone. And it ſhall be the better if you put a little freſh butter into it, and when they are boiled caſt ſpice vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make broth of Bettonie.</head>
                  <p>Take a few Bettonie leaues, and a little burrage, and put
<pb facs="tcp:5822:14"/>
them to boile in cleane ſéething water, then take them out and beat them with your knife, then take a little Parſely and Mint, and beat them with the ſaid hearbes, then ſtamp them all in a morter, and put them in a pipkin of fat broth, and let them boile, and if you will you may put a little Pepper to it, this may alſo be ſodden in oile.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth Gourdes after the Catalonian faſhion.</head>
                  <p>Take the iuice of the Gourd and make it very clean, then put it into a pipkin with good larde or oyle, and ſet the pipkin on the coales vpon a ſoft fire, and make it to boile, ſtirring it with a ſpoone: it ſhould ſéeth for the ſpace of foure houres, then take fat broth coloured with ſaffron, &amp; put into the Gourdes, adding thereto ſugar, ſpice, and a little Veriuice according to the taſt. You may alſo put to it a few yolkes of egges beaten together with a little old chéeſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Culleſſe of Capon, Feiſant, Partridge, Kid, or wild Pigeon.</head>
                  <p>Take of theſe Birds and make them very cleane, and if you would ſéeth a Capon til it conſume, and make two diſhes thereof, take a pipkin that holdeth foure pints of water, and breaking all the capons bones, put it therein and ſet it on the fire, and withall ſéeth a péece of leane Bacon with thirtie or forty grains of bruſed Pepper, a little ſinamon groſſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, a few cloues, thrée, fiue or ſixe ſage leaues broken in thrée péeces, and ſome bayleaues, let it boile in a pipkin, vntill it conſume to the quantity of two or thrée diſhes of broth, and leſſe if you will haue it good, but put no ſalt into it, and if it bee for a ſicke man, you muſt put no Bacon to, onely a little ſpice, and this is good both for the ſicke and whole.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:14"/>
                  <head>To make tenne diſhes of broth.</head>
                  <p>Take twenty yolkes of Egges, good veriuice, fleſh broth, or Capon broth which is better, a little Saffron, and ſome Spice, mingle them together and ſtraine them, then put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a pipkin, and ſet it on a ſoft fire, ſtirring it with a ſpoone, and when you ſée it ſticke to the ſpoone, take it from the fire, and forget not to ſtirre it, then diſh it, and ſtraw it with ſpice. It ſhould be ſwéet with ſugar, or ſharpe with veriuice, as you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make white broth.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of Almonds blanch them and ſtampe them in a morter, wherein you ſhall put a little faire water, that they be not oily, then take the white of twenty Egges, a few crummes of white bread, a little veriuice, ſome broth of fleſh or of a Capon, with a little white Ginger, &amp; beate them altogether, and ſtraine them with the Almonds, then ſéeth it well as I ſaid in the other broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make greene broth.</head>
                  <p>Take all the things ſet downe in the firſt broth, Saffron excepted and adde to them Bettonie, Parſely, and gréen corn if it be to be had, beat all this together, and ſtraine them and then ſéeth them as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a deuiſed broth.</head>
                  <p>Take twelue Egs, and a pound of good chéeſe wel grated, and mingle them together then take a pipkin full of broth of leane meat, coloured with ſaffron, and ſet it on the fire, and when it beginneth to boile, put theſe things into it, and ſtirre it with a ſpoone, and when it beginneth to bee thicke take it from the fire, and put ſpice vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:15"/>
                  <head>To make white pottage.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds ſtamped in a morter, and ſtraine them with broth, then take grated white bread, and the white of Egges, and put it into a pipkin, ſtirring it often, and then dreſſe it as I ſaid before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make greene meat.</head>
                  <p>Doe as I ſaid before, Saffron excepted, adding that which is aforeſaid of the gréene broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make greene, yellow, or other colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red meat in little peeces or morſels.</head>
                  <p>To make meat in ſmall péeces or morſels, of gréen or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, make them as aforeſaid according to the colour you wil haue, but ſomewhat harder, then take a little ſpoon, and with it make the meat into morſels as big as a Beane, and when the broth beginneth to ſéeth, put one by one into the broth, and being diſhed, ſtraw ſpice or ſugar on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a deuiſed meat after the Romane manner.</head>
                  <p>Take white floure, and make paſte of it ſomewhat thicker then a pancake, and roule it about a ſtaffe, then take out the ſtaffe, then cut the paſt in péeces of the length of thy little fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whereby they will bee hollow like a pudding and round or cloſe, then ſéeth them in fat broth or in water as time ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, but the broth or water muſt boile when you put them in. And if you ſéeth them in water put a little ſwéet Butter and ſalt in it, and when they are ſod, diſh them with Chéeſe, Butter, and ſpices.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:15"/>
                  <head>The ſame another way.</head>
                  <p>Make the paſt as before, and ſéeth them with the broth or water aforeſaid, but make the paſte ſomewhat thicker and cut it ſmal, and then they are called Trite, you may cut them alſo into greater péeces, and ſéeth them in the ſame manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make golden ſops.</head>
                  <p>Cut ſlices of white bread without cruſt, and make them ſquare, and toſt them a little before the fire, then take Egges very well beaten with a ſpoone and a little Roſe-water, and then put the ſaid ſlices to ſoke therin, then take them out and fry them in a fryingpan with a little Butter, turning them very oft for feare of burning, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n put them in a diſh, and caſt a little roſewater on them coloured yellow with ſaffron and ſugar, and ſo ſend them to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a fried meat of Turneps.</head>
                  <p>Roſt the Turnops in the embers, or elſe ſéeth them whole, then cut or ſlice them in péeces as thicke as halfe the haft of a knife, which done, take chéeſe and cut it in the ſame form and quantity, but ſome what thinner, then take Sugar, Pepper, and other ſpices mingled togither, and put them in a pan vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the péeces of chéeſe, as if you would make a cruſt vnder the chéeſe, and on the top of them likewiſe, and ouer it you ſhall lay the péeces of Turneps, couering them ouer with the ſpices aforeſaid, and plenty of good Butter, and ſo you ſhall doe with the ſaid chéeſe and Turneps till the pan bée full, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them fry the ſpace of a quarter of an houre, or more, like a Tart, and this would be one of your laſt diſhes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:5822:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The third Booke:</hi> Shewing how to dreſse fiſh, hearbs, and many other things in Lent time.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make tenne meſſe of white meat in Lent.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake a pound and a halfe of blanched Almonds and ſtampe them, and the crums of a white loafe ſtéeped in broth of white peaſe. If you haue no peaſe broth, you may ſéeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breadin water for the ſpace of halfe an houre, making it ſoft, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take ſome good ſea fiſh or Pike (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the riuer) ſodden, then take halfe a pound of the white meat of the fiſh, and ſtampe it with the Almonds, ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den bread, a litle broth, and the iuice of Orenges, if you haue no Orenges take Veriuice, with ſome Roſewater, and half a pound of cleane white Ginger, and halfe a pound of ſugar, all theſe tempered together and ſtrained, you ſhall ſet them to ſéeth in a pipkin with a ſoft fire for the ſpace of half a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an houre, and let it not ſmell of the ſmoke, but ſtirre it often.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth Rice pottage in Lent.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of blanched Almonds, and a pound of rice waſhed twiſe or thriſe in luke warme water, and ſet them on the fire in cleare water, make it ſéeth as is aforeſaid in the ſecond chapter of meat made of Rice, but you ſhal not ſéeth it with fleſh broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:16"/>
                  <head>To make eight meſſes of Almond broth.</head>
                  <p>Take two pound of blanched Almonds, and ſtampe them well and temper them with cold water, becauſe they ſhal not be oily, put to them the crummes of a white loafe, then ſtrain them and ſet them to boile in a pipkin vpon the coales, and let it boile for halfe a quarter of an houre, putting into them a pound of fine ſugar. This Almond broth would bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what liquid by adding a little Roſewater to it, and it will bee ſo much the better, and ſo ſend it to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make broth of Hempe-ſeed.</head>
                  <p>You ſhal follow the order aforeſaid, only that you ſhal not vſe fleſh broth, but fiſh or peaſe broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make broth of peaſe.</head>
                  <p>You may ſéeth peaſe likewiſe with Almond milk in Lent time as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To fry peaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Peaſe in the huſkes and boile them, then take good oyle, and fry it a little, wherein you ſhal put the peaſe and fry them in it, adding veriuice, new wine, or ſugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make pottage of Beanes.</head>
                  <p>Take Beanes a little broken, make them very cleane and ſet them on the fire, and when the water boileth caſt it away, and put more water that it may bee higher then the Beanes by two fingers, then caſting in ſome ſalt, ſet them to ſéeth vpon the coales on a ſoft fire, couering them, and let them boile well: that done, dry them, and ſtampe them in a
<pb facs="tcp:5822:17"/>
morter, then boile them againe in a pipkin with good oyle, and let them ſéeth well, but burne them not, then take a little ſage and ſigges, or apples cut ſmall, and put it into the Oyle with Onyons, and ſofty them, then diſh them and put ſome of the oyle and other mixtures vpon them with good ſpices.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To fry Beanes in a pan.</head>
                  <p>Take Beanes, Sage, Onions, and Figges as aforeſaied, with other good hearbes, and mingle them together, then frie them in a frying pan with oyle, and make it like a pancake, and when it is baked take it out, and caſt ſpice vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ten meſſes of good broth made of red Peaſe or Cicers.</head>
                  <p>Take two pound of peaſe and waſh them in whote wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and put them into a pipkin, firſt drying them put to them an ounce of floure, oyle, ſalt, Pepper, and a little Sinamon well beaten, ſtirre all with a ſpoone. Then put to them three quarts of water or more, with a little S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge, Roſemary, and Parſely rootes, and let them boile together till it bee conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the quantity of tenne meſſes, and when it is almoſt boiled, adde to it a little more oile, but if you make it for a ſick perſon, you ſhall put neither oyle nor ſpice into it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a deuiſed meat of Almonds.</head>
                  <p>Take two pound of Almonds and ſtampe them well, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering them with cold water leaſt they bee oily, then take crummes of white bread and ſoke it in veriuice, then take the Almonds, crummes of Bread, iuice of Orenges, and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and temper all together, adding an ounce of ſinamon and a pound of fine ſugar, and ſtraine all this together, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it yellow with ſaffron. And ſet it to boile in a pipkin vpon coales with a ſoft fire, and let it not take ſmoke, ſtirring
<pb facs="tcp:5822:17"/>
it often with a ſpoone, and ſo let it boile for the ſpace of halfe a quarter of an houre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ten meſſe of a compound broth.</head>
                  <p>Firſt take two pound of Almonds ſtamped with a few el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der floures, and temper them with freſh water, then ſtraine them, and when they are ſtrained, put them in a pipkin to ſéeth: then take a quart of raw milk, and put into it thrée oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Dill, and crummes of white bread, this you ſhall beate togither with a pound of ſugar, and ſet it to ſéeth, &amp; when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to boile, you ſhall mingle them with the other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, but ſtirre it not, and when it is mixed &amp; waxeth thick, then diſh it, ſtrawing ſpice vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make twelue meſſes of pottage of elder flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take two pound of Almonds and ſtampe them as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, then take foure ounces of dry elder floures, and let them ſoke in clean water for the ſpace of an houre, then wring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the water, and ſtampe them with the Almonds, adding to it the crummes of a white loafe, and a pound of ſugar. And if you will haue them yellow caſt ſaffron in them, then ſtrain it and ſet it to ſéeth as aforeſaid, and being on the fire, caſt ſome of the ſaid flowers whole vpon it, and when it is boyled, ſpice it well. If you will make this broth in fleſh time, you muſt adde yolkes of egges with fat broth of a Pullet or other good broth, and ſtraine it with ſugar and other ſpices, and the floures of elders as aforeſaid, and being halfe boiled, put into it thrée ounces of ſwéet butter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat of Egges beaten, which ſhall ſhew like peaſe.</head>
                  <p>Séeth your Egges a little, then take them out of the broth
<pb facs="tcp:5822:18"/>
and to make the broth ſomewhat thicke, take the crummes of a white loafe and ſtraine it through the water, or elſe take the broth of Peaſe it ſelfe if you can get it, for it is better, and in any of theſe two brothes you ſhall ſéeth your egges again, with ſome ſpice, ſaffron, parſely and Mint minced very ſmal.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a deuiſed diſh of meat or broth, of hearbes and Almonds.</head>
                  <p>Take hearbes and boyle them, but let the water boile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you put them in, then take them out and lay them on a Table or a trencher, and cut them ſmall with a knife, then beat them in a morter, and then boile them in almond milke, adding ſugar vnto it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a diſh of hearbes without milke.</head>
                  <p>Boile your hearbes as aforeſaid, and with ſome fat or lean broth as time ſerueth, make your diſhes as you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Gourds with Almond milke or with other milke.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the Gourdes in water, then preſſe the water out of them and ſtraine them, then ſéeth them with almond milke or other milke, with ſugar, and a little veriuice as you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To fry Gourdes or Pompeons.</head>
                  <p>Take Gourdes and make them very cleane, then cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thinne péeces, and let them boile one waume, then take them out and dry them and ſalt them, rouling them in floure, that done, fry them in good oile, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take them off the fire, and take a little Garlike and crummes of bread and ſtampe them together with a little Veriuice, then ſtraine it, and put this
<pb facs="tcp:5822:18"/>
ſauce vpon the Gourds, it will be good if you put nothing but Veriuice, Fennell ſéed, and a little bafill: and if you will haue it yellow, caſt ſaffron into it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make pottage of Lettuce which ſhall ſeeme to be Gourd.</head>
                  <p>Take the white &amp; inward part of Lettuce, which is in the middle of them, and ſéeth them with onyons, Veriuice, pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſaffron, if you wil make it in fleſh time boile them in fleſh broth as is aforeſaid with egges and veriuice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make pottage of Coleworts after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Rome.</head>
                  <p>Open the Coleworts, and cut the leaues as it is vſually done, and boile them in water, and when they are halfe boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, take them out and caſt that water away, &amp; put the Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts into a quantity of oyle, firſt letting them dry, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the oyle ſtirre them with a ſpoone: then take fiſh broth and boile them in it as much as you think good, but if you wil ſéeth them in fleſh time, boile them in fleſh broth with ſalt fleſh or bacon, for they would be fat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe muſhromes.</head>
                  <p>Make the Muſhromes very cleane, and ſéeth them with two or thrée heads of Garlike, and crummes of bread, &amp; this is done becauſe naturally they are venomous, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take them vp, and let the water runne out of them vntil they be dry, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fry them in oyle, and when they are fried, caſt pepper and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpices on them, in fleſh time fry them as aforeſaied. You may dreſſe them another way, make them very cleane, then ſet them on the fire, putting to them larde and Garlike bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten together, with pepper, you may likewiſe dreſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with oyle, you may fry them alſo in a frying pan like a pancake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:19"/>
                  <head>To make a kind of boiled meat or ſauce to eat vvith fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds and Currans according to the quantity of the fiſh, with nuts, and ſtampe them together, and ſtraine them if you think good, then take pepper &amp; other ſpices, a few cloues, Veriuice, and ſaffron, and boile them together, then fry your fiſh with good oyle, and then put the foreſaid things vpon it, and when it is fried caſt a good quantity of Sinamon vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, this meat is beſt cold: you may take fat broth without veriuice, and it will be good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make all kind of ſauce, and firſt of vvhite ſauce.</head>
                  <p>Take what quantity of almonds you think good blanched, &amp; ſtamp them, &amp; becauſe they ſhal be oily, temper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with cold water, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take crums of white bread, according to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity you will make, and let it ſoke in veriuice, then ſtampe it with the Almonds, with ſome white Ginger, then ſtraine it with Veriuice, or the iuice of Orenges or Lemmonds, and make it ſwéet or ſoure as you think good, this ſauce will ſerue for all boiled meat in fleſh time, and likewiſe to fiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another ſauce.</head>
                  <p>Take Currans and ſtampe them in a morter, then take toſted bread ſtéeped in Red wine, according to the quantity you will haue, and ſtampe them together, then take a little Red wine, Veriuice, with other baſtard wine, or with Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger if you will not haue veriuice, &amp; ſtraine it, making it ſwéet or ſower as you think good, and put to it ſinamon, cloues, and Nutmegs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another ſauce.</head>
                  <p>Take the yolke of Egges almoſt hard, Chickins or Hens
<pb facs="tcp:5822:19"/>
liuers, ſodden &amp; ſcorched, Almonds according to the quantity you will haue, beat them in a morter, &amp; temper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice or vineger, then ſtraine them, adding Sinamon, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Sugar: this ſauce would be a little boyled, and colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with ſaffron.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of dry proins.</head>
                  <p>Take Proines and ſtéep them in Clarret wine, then take out the ſtones, and ſtampe them with a few blanched Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and a toſte of bread ſoked in the wine wherein the Proines were ſtéeped, ſtampe all this together, tempering them with a little veriuice and other baſtard wine, or Sugar which is better, then ſtraine them, and put ſpice vnto them, ſpecially Sinamon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>If you vvill make greene ſauce looke in the chapter before, vvhere it is ſet downe, follovv the order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in preſcribed.</head>
                  <p>Take Parſely, wild Time, and Mint, with other good hearbes, adding to them Salt, Pepper, and Ginger, beate them together, and temper it with ſtrong Vineger, then ſtraine them: and if you will haue it taſt of Garlike, beate ſome heads of Garlike with it, as much as you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a ſauce called Perſico.</head>
                  <p>Take blanched Almonds well ſtamped with crummes of White bread, and a little Ginger, Sinamon, Veriuice, Clarret wine, the iuice of Pomgranets, and a little San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, temper them together and ſtraine them with a little Red wine, and then make it ſwéet or ſoure as you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:20"/>
                  <head>To make ſauce called the floures of broome.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds, Saffron, and yolkes of Egges, and let the Almonds be blanched and beaten as they ſhould be, then temper them with veriuice, adding Ginger well beaten.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of grapes.</head>
                  <p>Take blacke grapes and bruſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a morter with ſome bread, according to the quantity you will haue, then temper them with a little Veriuice or Vineger, becauſe the grapes ſhould not be too ſwéet, then ſéeth them for the ſpace of halfe an houre with Sinamon, Ginger, and other ſpice,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of mulberies.</head>
                  <p>Take blanched Almonds well beaten with crummes of bread, then take the Mulberies and mixe them together, but not in a morter leaſt you breake the ſmall grain or ſéed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Mulbery, then put to it Sinamon and Nutmeg, and ſtraine them all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of red or blacke Cherries.</head>
                  <p>Vſe them as you did the grapes, but you may make it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by ſéething it more or leſſe according to the quantity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of Barberies.</head>
                  <p>To make this ſauce, follow the order proſcribed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauce made of Cherries and grapes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make iuice of Barberies to keepe all the Winter.</head>
                  <p>Take ripe Barbaries, and with thy hand bruſe them into
<pb facs="tcp:5822:20"/>
a pipkin or other veſſell and to them put new veriuice, Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſalt plenty, and boile them for the ſpace of two hours or more, and then ſtrain it, and kéep it in a veſſell, it would be well ſalted, &amp; this will be good iuice to colour any other ſauce that you will make.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make muſtard.</head>
                  <p>Take muſtard ſéed &amp; let it ſoke for the ſpace of two daies, and change the water often, that it may be the whiter, then take blanched Almonds ſtamped in a morter, and when they are ſtamped put the muſtard ſéed to them and ſtamp them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, adding veriuice or vineger, with crummes of white bread, and being tempered together, ſtraine them and make it ſharpe as you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make muſtard after the manner of Padoa.</head>
                  <p>Take muſtard ſéede and beate it very ſmall, then take Grapes well ſtamped, adding to it a toſt of white bread, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sanders, Sinamon, veriuice or vineger, &amp; baſtard wine, temper this together and ſtraine it. Made by maiſter <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Trombone.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make muſtard vvhich may be carried in Bals.</head>
                  <p>Beat the muſtard ſéed as aforeſaid, then take grapes well ſtamped, adding thereto Sinamon and Cloues, then make what faſhion bals you will round or ſquare, and ſet them on a table to dry, and being dry, you may carry them whether you will. And when you will vſe them, temper them with a little veriuice, vineger, ſodden wine, or Baſtard wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a skie colour ſauce in ſummer.</head>
                  <p>Take wild mulberies which grow in the Hedges, and a
<pb facs="tcp:5822:21"/>
few ſtamped Almonds with a little Ginger, temper all this with Veriuice and ſtraine it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make yellow ſauce.</head>
                  <p>Take bread cut in ſlices and toſt it, then take red Wine, a little vineger and ſodden wine, put the bread into it, and let it ſéeth, then ſtraine it and put ſpice into it, and colour it with ſaffron.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make good garlike ſauce.</head>
                  <p>Take blanched Almonds well ſtamped, and being halfe beaten, put as much Garlike to them as you thinke good, and ſtampe them together, tempering them with water leaſt it bee oiley, then take crummes of white bread what quantity you will, and ſoke it either in leane broth of fleſh or fiſh as time ſerueth: this ſauce you may kéepe &amp; vſe with all meats, fat or leane as you thinke good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make garlike ſauce in grape or Cherry time.</head>
                  <p>You muſt follow the order preſcribed in the chapter afore, only that you muſt adde no broth, but take black grapes, and bruſe them well with thy hand into a pipkin or other veſſell, then let them boyle for halfe an houre, and ſtraine them, and mix this iuice with your garlike: it may be vſed in fleſh time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make greene Veriuice.</head>
                  <p>Take grapes and Sorrell, or Veriuice, and ſtampe them with a little Salt, you muſt haue a little old Veriuice, wherewith you may temper and ſtraine it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make veriuice of Fennel-ſeed.</head>
                  <p>Take Garlike if you will, and Fennel-ſéed the beſt you
<pb facs="tcp:5822:21"/>
can get, beat and boyle them together, adding thereto annis ſéed, with new Veriuice, and with this veriuice you ſhal tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſtraine it, and let it be ſomewhat ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of yong Roſes.</head>
                  <p>The Roſes would be ſomewhat gréene and not ouer ripe, and when you haue ſtamped them very well by themſelues, ſtampe them once again with a head of Garlike if you think good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="book">
               <head>The fourth Booke: Shewing how to dreſſe all kind of Fiſh.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Treatiſe it is generally to bee noted, that all fiſh either to be ſodden or fried, muſt firſt haue the ſcales taken off and cut on the outſide, then opened and the guts taken out and clean waſhed: but the fiſh which you wil roſt would not be ſcaled, ſcraped, opened, nor the guts taken out, but well waſhed and opened, ſalt fiſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, which would bee opened and the inwards taken out, likewiſe you muſt take out the guts of maids or Thorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backes by the gils with a forke or ſtring, the which is faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto a gut within, which muſt be taken out either ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or broiling it.</p>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:22"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe a Carpe.</head>
                  <p>Firſt make good pickle, ſuch as commonly is made for ſalt fiſh or ſouſed fiſh, then take the Carpe and put it into the pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, and let it ſtand two daies, then fry him in oyle, and ſo you may kéepe it twenty daies or a month, and then fry him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe as you think good, and the more and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener it is fried, the more it loſeth of his ſubſtance, and are the worſe: And therefore this way is onely to make him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long, and if they be great ſéeth them, if ſmall fry them, but take héed there bee none of the bone left in the head, for it is venemous.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Sturgion.</head>
                  <p>If you will haue it good and in perfection, let it not bée too new, but let it mortifie for a time, then take white Wine or Vineger mixed with water, as much of the one as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, and ſalt as much as ſufficeth, wherin you ſhall ſéeth it as long as you vſe to ſéeth veale or Mutton, according to the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; cut it into great péeces ſuch as may not eaſily breake but ſéeth whole, for all fiſh is better whole then in péeces. The ſauce would be white, mixed with Ginger, very white Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or Muſtard as time ſerueth, or mens appetites require, which you ſhall make as aforeſaid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtruction for ſauces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Latus or ſhadovv fiſh.</head>
                  <p>It is dreſſed like Sturgion, onely it requireth not ſo long ſéething, and ſhall haue the like ſauce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Sangris or tooth fiſh.</head>
                  <p>It is beſt ſodden, but it muſt bee freſh, you néed not put ſo much wine to it, but vineger, becauſe it bindeth and maketh fiſh continue the longer, giuing it a better taſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:22"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe a Baſe.</head>
                  <p>Séeth this fiſh as aforeſaid, but if it waieth leſſe then four or fiue pound fry it in good oile, or broile it on a gredyron, but remember as aforeſaid that when you fry it, it muſt neither bee ſcraped nor opened, and you muſt make a kind of liquor with vineger, oyle, and Salt, and with a Roſemary branch, baſt it there with vpon the gredyron, turning it often and let it broile very wel and leiſurely, for all fiſh would be wel broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or ſodden, otherwiſe it is vnholeſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a glaucus or <hi>corbo groſſo</hi> fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Séeth it as aforeſaid, but if it it way but four or fiue pounds fry it in oyle or broyle it on a gredyron with ſcraping or ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it: for ſauce take gréene ſauce ſauoring of Garlike, and Ginger, if you will you may eat it with muſtard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Gilthead or gilden pole.</head>
                  <p>If it be great boyle it, and ſeaſon it well, if it bee little fry it or roſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Burt or Turbut.</head>
                  <p>Séeth it becauſe it is very looſe and brittle, and will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall in péeces, but if you will kéepe it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breaking put it in a ſmall baſket, or lay it on a trencher, that you may take it out whole, it muſt be ſodden with great leiſure, and all fiſh would bee ſodden with diſcretion, for ſome fiſhes are hard and more ſolid then others, and therefore they muſt be ſod according to their quality, but generally all fiſh would bee very wel ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and with leiſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſauce of vine branches.</head>
                  <p>Take vine branches and ſtampe them, and if you wil you
<pb facs="tcp:5822:23"/>
may adde a few Garlike leaues, with crummes of white bread, according to the quantity you wil make, and ſalt: this done, temper them together with Vineger or Veriuice, and then ſtraine it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Dab.</head>
                  <p>It muſt be fried, then caſt ouer it a little Salt and iuice of Orenges or Veriuice, with Parſely chopped very ſmall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Palmita, vvhich is a kind of Tonny.</head>
                  <p>Séeth it like a Sturgion, and giue it the like ſauce, being little it would be fried, for it cannot bee roſted becauſe it hath no ſcales, and if you wil fry it cut it in round ſlices halfe a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thicke, and fry it well, putting to it good ſtore of the iuice of Orenges, with ſpices and a little Parſely if you think good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Treglie a kind of Barble.</head>
                  <p>It would be well roſted and not opened, but waſhed and often baſted with the liquor aforeſaid, and if you will kéepe it eight or tenne daies, lay two or thrée one vpon the other in a platter, with as much liquor on them as may couer them, and ſo you may kéepe them long.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Goldſtrike.</head>
                  <p>It is good both ſodden and roſted or fried if it bee great or little as you thinke good: the ſauce is greene ſauce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Sapony another kind of Goldſtrike.</head>
                  <p>It would of nature bee fried, all the guts firſt being taken out, for it hath many, and when you will roſt it take out his entrailes and make as little a hole as you can.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:23"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe Smelts.</head>
                  <p>Boyle them, for of themſelues they are better that way then any other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a ſcorpion of the ſea.</head>
                  <p>If it be great it would be ſodden: if little, fried.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a ſea Breame.</head>
                  <p>They are better fried or roſted then ſodden.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a ſea Trout.</head>
                  <p>It is good roſted or ſodden as you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a kind of Sturgion called Moreca, or a ſea ſerpent.</head>
                  <p>Firſt flea it with whote water, and caſt away the head and taile, and fry it well: and for ſauce vſe gréene ſauce with Garlike.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Macarell.</head>
                  <p>They will be fried, &amp; yet they are good ſodden with Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Parſely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Muler.</head>
                  <p>This fiſh of nature would be roſted, but if he be very great ſéeth it, and the ſauce to the roſted is the liquor aforeſaid, and Fennell-ſéed, and to the boyled white ſauce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Plaice.</head>
                  <p>It would be boiled with a little parſely, and it is alſo good fried, putting on it the iuice of Orenges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Beſano an Italian fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Boyle it in wine, or Vineger and water, of ech a like, and for ſauce take Garlike, but this courſe fiſh is fitter for labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring men then men of any quality.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Dogfiſh.</head>
                  <p>It would be ſodden as aforeſaid, &amp; then with ſtrong gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and a little muſtard, fry it in a pan, but dreſſe it in what ſort you will, it will neuer bée good as being naturally of no good taſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:24"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe Eeles.</head>
                  <p>A great Eele would be roſted, being firſt flead and made clean, and then cut in great péeces of a handfull long or leſſe, and when you ſpit it, betwéene ech péece put a ſage or a Bay leafe, and turn the ſpit very ſoftly, and baſt it with the pirkle ſpoken of before, and when it is almoſt roſted, crum it with bread mixed with a little Sinamon &amp; Salt, which will make it haue a little cruſt, that giueth them a good taſt: you may ſéeth ſmall Eeles in Water, Wine, Hearbes, and Spices as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Mochie, an Italian fiſh.</head>
                  <p>It would be ſodden like a Creuiſh of the riuer, and ſhould be eaten with vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Sea Creuiſh.</head>
                  <p>Séeth it likewiſe with Fennell, and eat it with Vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Oyſters.</head>
                  <p>They are to bee roſted on the coales, and when they open they are inough, you may take them alſo out of the ſhell, and fry them in oile, and eat them with vineger and Pepper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Lampernes.</head>
                  <p>It will be fried with the iuice of an Orenge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a ſhad or Pilchare.</head>
                  <p>It is good roſted, but firſt pull out entrailes and guts, and eat it with gréen ſauce, it is alſo good ſodden, but then it muſt haue white ſauce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Muskels or Cockles.</head>
                  <p>Take a frying pan and ſet them ouer the fire, and when they open they are ready, and as you ſée them open, put in a little Veriuice, Pepper and Parſely ſhred ſmall, and turne them in the panne. You may roſt them on a hote yron vpon the coales, and when they open they are roſted. But they would be kept a day &amp; a night in ſalt water before you dreſſe them, that the ſand within them may bée gotten out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:24"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe a Whiting.</head>
                  <p>Séeth them and eat them with white muſtard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Pike.</head>
                  <p>Take out the guts and if it be great ſéeth it, but ſcrape him not vntill he be ſodden, the ſauce is white ſauce, Garlike, and muſtard, but if he bée a little one, fry it, it may bee broyled on the gredyron, and ſtuffed with good hearbes and Currans.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Barble.</head>
                  <p>Vſe it as you will, but it is not thought to be fiſh, and the Spawne is dangerous to be eaten, and chiefly in May.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Grayling.</head>
                  <p>This is excellent good fiſh, dreſſe it as you will, for it is good euery way, but it is beſt boyled.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe <hi>Corario marino,</hi> a kind of ſea Breame.</head>
                  <p>Roſt it as you doe an Eele, with ſage or bay leaues betwixt euery péece.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Creuiſſe.</head>
                  <p>Boyle them in water and vineger with much ſalt, becauſe they themſelues yéeld much water, therfore put not too much liquor to them, and let them ſéeth wel vntil they yéeld a great ſkim. And when they are boiled in that maner twiſe or thrice they are inough, but proue them firſt leaſt you be deceiued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Creuiſſes full of compound meat.</head>
                  <p>Dreſſe them as aforeſaid, and open their belly cunningly with a knife betwixt their legges, and take out all the meate out of their bellies, tailes and féet, which done, ſtamp it with Almonds, Currans, and yolkes of Egges, according to the quantity you will make with ſome chéeſe, Perſely, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerum, ſtamped ſmall together, and with this compound fill the Creuiſhes again, &amp; ſéeth them again in good oyle, as ſoftly as you may: if it bee Lent adde no Egges nor Chéefe. And if you wil fill them with variety, take Almonds ſtamped with Sugar and roſewater, and fill the féet with one kind, and the other parts with another kind of meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:25"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe the fiſh called the Lion of the ſea.</head>
                  <p>Stop their mouthes and the hole which they haue vnder their tailes wih cotton, becauſe their ſwéetneſſe may not run out, and put them dry in an ouen to bake leiſurely, or lay them vpon the hearth well heated &amp; ſwept, making a fire of coales round about them, but not too néere becauſe they may bee the better roſted and the ſooner, and turne them ott leaſt they turne. And if you wil you may ſéeth them in water and vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger like Creuiſſes, but let them ſéeth ſomewhat more as you ſée cauſe, for they are harder and bigger then other creuiſſes, and for ſauce take vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth the Horne-becke or Pipe fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Stop their holes and dreſſe them likewiſe as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Breame.</head>
                  <p>Dreſſe it as you will, but it is little eſtéemed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Carpe.</head>
                  <p>If they be great boyle them, you may alſo take them and fry them being ſmall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Salmon.</head>
                  <p>Salmon is an excellent fiſh, and ſhould ordinarily be ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, yet it is good any other way.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Mugilis, in Italian <hi>Laſche.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>They ſhould be ſoftly fried leaſt they burne, and eat them with gréene ſauce or Veriuice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a kind of Hering, in Italian <hi>Lattacini.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>You muſt fry the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; eat them with gréen ſauce or veriuice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe <hi>Ruvoglioni,</hi> an Italian fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Fry them alſo, and giue them the ſame ſauce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe <hi>Bachie Coſalze,</hi> an Italian fiſh.</head>
                  <p>His nature is to be fried or ſodden, it is alſo good roſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Turdus.</head>
                  <p>If it be great boyle it, if little fry it, and for ſauce take muſtard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:25"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe <hi>Agoni</hi> diuers waies, an Italian fiſh.</head>
                  <p>They are good ſodden with Parſely, Butter, Spice, they are good alſo fried with the iuice of Orenges and Veriuice mingled with oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Cuttle fiſh.</head>
                  <p>This fiſh is of no account, &amp; therefore dreſſe it as you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Crabs.</head>
                  <p>Do as I haue ſaid of creuiſſe, and eat them with vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Pearch.</head>
                  <p>If it be great take out the guts and ſéeth it, but ſcrape it not, if it be freſh ſéeth it in cleane water and Vineger, and when it is ſodden take off the ſcales, but if it be little ſcrape it and dreſſe it in oyle, it is good fried being baſted with liquor as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Tench three waies.</head>
                  <p>Tenches are good thrée manner of waies, firſt ſodden if they bee well growen, and for ſauce you may make a little broth with Veriuice, Spice, and Parſely chopped very ſmal with the broth of the ſame Tench. The ſecond is to cut and cleaue it in the backe foom the head to the taile, and if it bee great you ſhall firſt ſcrape it, and when hee is clouen cut the rige bone on both ſides and ſéeth the Spawne, fat, and liuer thereof, and if the Tench haue none, the Spawne, fat or liuer of another fiſh will ſerue, then take Parſely and margerum, and other ſwéet hearbes, and beat them all together with the liuer, Spawne and fat, putting to it a little Garlike chopped ſmall with ſome Pepper, Saffron, Salt, &amp; a little oile, as alſo Proines, Cherries, Currans, or the kernels of a Pine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and yolks of Egs as time ſerueth, al this tempered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſhall put vpon the Tench on the outſide, then ſow it vp with a needle and thread, or elſe tie and bind about with a packtbred, ſo that the compoſitions may not run foorth, then lay it on the gredyron with ſoft fire vnder it that it may roſt at leiſure, and make a liquor with Vineger, Oyle, Salt, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron
<pb facs="tcp:5822:26"/>
and Pepper, and a little broken wine, and as you turne it, baſt it well with this liquor. The third way is, that if the Tench bee ſmall, ſcrape it well and cut it open at the backe, and caſt ſalt vpon him, then throw flower vpon all ſides, and fry it in oyle, and for ſauce take the iuice of orenges or veriuice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a great Trout.</head>
                  <p>Make it very cleane and cut it ouerthwart in round péeces of the bigneſſe of your hand, and lay euery péece flat by itſelf in the Chaldren or pan wherein you will ſéeth them, putting good ſtore of ſalt into the pan vpon them, this done, pour wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo eaſily vnto them that it waſheth not away the ſalt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon them, with as much vineger, as that the liquor may be thrée fingers aboue the fiſh, and ſo let it boyle, ſkimming it very well: and when it hath left ſkimming, abate the fire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, that it may boyle ſoftly til it be ynough, then take it out and lay it vpon a drie cleane table, caſting ſpice vpon it. To this Trout you may vſe white ſauce with Ginger. When it is little make it cleane, and cut ſlices on both ſides, and into the cuts put ſalt, then preſſe it betwixt two trenchers, laying ſome waight vpon it, and ſo let it reſt for the ſpace of two or thrée houres, then caſt floure on it and fry it leiſurely in good oyle, and ſo you may keepe it thrée or foure daies if you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Lamprey.</head>
                  <p>Lay it to ſoke in hote water, and ſcrape off the ſlime, but breake not the ſkin, and take out the tongue and téeth, and in the bottome of his belly you muſt make a little hole, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in put the end of your finger, and with a knife or pricke of wood, you ſhall take out the gut or ſtring, and pull it out with a cloth ſoftly that it be not broken: For the Lamprey hath no euil thing in it, but only his ſtring. For ſauce you muſt keepe the blood, for it is the right ſauce, in the mouth you ſhall put halfe a nutmeg, and in ech hole which he hath about his head
<pb facs="tcp:5822:26"/>
you ſhall ſticke a Cloue, and ſo roule it in a ring and put it in an earthen veſſell, wherein you muſt put halfe an ounce of good Oyle, a little Veriuice, a little White wine the beſt you can get, making as much of the liquor as will couer more then halfe the Lamprey, then caſt a little ſalt vpon it, and ſo bake it leiſurely vpon the coales like a Tarte. When it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to bake, open the holes with a knife, and with a tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher preſſe it downe ſo hard, that the blood may come foorth, which you muſt mingle with the other things. And if you thinke good you may eaſily take out the blood before you ſet it on the fire. And for ſauce take Almonds or Nuts, vnblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched but put them vnder the whote embers, then pill them and ſtampe them with a few Currans and a péece of toſted bread tempered with Veriuice and broken wine, with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the wine or liquor aforeſaid, wherein the Lamprey is ſodden, and when all this is ſtrained put to it ſome Ginger, Cloues, and Sinamon. Alſo if you take out the blood before it is ſodden, you muſt mingle it with thoſe forſaid things, which you ſhall ſéeth with the Lamprey vntill it be well ſodden, and then you ſhall roule it with the ſauce, and laying it in a diſh ſend it to the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>You may dreſſe it another way vpon a ſpit.</head>
                  <p>When it is roſting ſet a diſh vnder it to receiue the blood, fat, and liquor that commeth out of it, which is the beſt of the ſubſtance, then you may make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauce aforeſaid for it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you may fry it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>When they be little they ſhould be broiled.</head>
                  <p>They ſhould bee broiled vpon a gredyron at leiſure, with ſauce of the iuice of Orenges and broken wine, if you will haue no Orenges take Veriuice, Salt, Oyle, and Spice. And when they are broyling baſt them with the ſaid ſauce, and when they are broiled, put of the ſame ſauce vpon them, and ſend them to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:27"/>
                  <head>To dreſſe an Inke horne fiſh, in Latine <hi>Lolligo.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The leſſe they bee the better they are, waſh them very clean and ſtuffe them as you do the Tench being turned out, and if you can deuiſe a better ſtuffing you may, then fry them in oyle, and put the iuice of Orenges vpon them with ſpices. You may ſéeth the great fiſhes, cutting them in péeces like ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Veale or Béefe, and boile them in broth with Parſely ſhred ſmal and Spices. If they be great, you may dreſſe them another way. Firſt waſh him in white Wine &amp; a little ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice, with this kind of waſhing you may get out the blacke iuice whereof the ſauce is made, then take Almonds roſted vnder the embers according to the quantity, and ſtamp them in a morter with toſted bread, and ſo temper it with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aforeſaid, then ſtraine it and boyle it, putting thereto Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, and a few Cloues. And when it is fried you ſhall put this ſauce vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth, fry, and broile a Pike or any other fiſh all at one time.</head>
                  <p>Take a great fiſh and pull out the guts, and make it very cleane, then bind a third part of it towards the head with a wet cloth, for that part that ſhould bee ſodden muſt bee coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then goe to the taile and ſcrape it to the quantity of a third part and cut it on both ſides like a fried fiſh, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fry this part of the taile in ſuch ſort that you ſpoile or touch not the reſt of this fiſh, this being done, you muſt haue a thinne bord of the bigneſſe of the middle of the fiſh, vpon the which you ſhal bind the ſaid fiſh ſo ſoftly that it breaketh not, then ſéeth that part of the fiſh which is bound with the cloth that is the head, and let not the broth touch any more of the fiſh then that which is wrapped in the cloth, and when this part is well boyled, take it out and looſe it ſoftly from the bord that it breake not. Then lay it on a gredyron vpon the coales
<pb facs="tcp:5822:27"/>
with fire only vnder the middle part which is not ſodden nor fried, and let it touch no part elſe, and that the fire may not hurt the fried and boyled part of the fiſh, you muſt take two ſquare ſtones made for the purpoſe, and put them vnder the gredyron, and lay the coales betwixt them, and in broyling the fiſh baſt it with the liquor aforeſaid, which is fit for broy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fiſh, and when it is ready take it from the fire, and vntie the cloth that is wrapped about the head, and making it cleane you ſhall ſend it to the Table. If you will you may make thrée kind of ſauces, for it is fit for ſodden, fried, &amp; broy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe <hi>Schinale</hi> an Italian fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Cut it croſſewaies of the bigneſſe of halfe a finger or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, and make it very cleane round about, then broile it on a gredyron and turn it often, and baſt it continually with oile and vineger mingled together, as much of the one as of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but it would not be much roſted nor very dry. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you think that the fire hath perched it and changed the colour thereof round about it is roſted, then ſend it to the Table. To know when it is broiled cut it, and if it bee red within it is y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but looke it be not ouerſtale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a kind of meat of the ſpawne of Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, called Chauiale.</head>
                  <p>Take bread and toſt it vntill it begin to chaunge colour, and cut ſome of the ſpawne in péeces as great as the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the bread, but ſomewhat thinner, and lay it vpon the bread, then ſticke the toſts vpon a knifes point or ſome other thing, and hold them to the fire vntill the ſpawne waxe hard and ſomewhat change colour. You may doe it another way by waſhing the ſpawne of the Sturgion in warme water, that it be not too ſalt, then take hearbs chopped with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crums of white bread grated, and Onyons minced ſmall, and fried with a little pepper and a diſh of water, then mingle all theſe
<pb facs="tcp:5822:28"/>
things together with the Spawne, and it will be like a Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cake, and ſo frie it like a Tanſie of Egges. And to prepare this Chauiale you muſt take the Spawnes of Sturgions when the Sturgion is beſt in ſeaſon, and take out the ſinews that are in them, then waſh them with white Vineger, and let them dry vpon a Table, then put them into ſome veſſell, and ſalt them with diſcretion, and ſtir them with your hand but very warily that you breake them not, that done, take a linnen bag ſomewhat thinne, and put the Chauiale into it for a day and a night, that the ſalt water may run out, then put them into ſome veſſell or other, and preſſe them very well with thy hands, making thrée or foure little holes in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the veſſell, by the which the moiſture may iſſue out, and being well ſtrained, kéepe the veſſell very cloſe. And ſo you may eat of them at your pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Trouts in manner of Carpes.</head>
                  <p>Make the Trout very clean, taking out the guts, pricking it in many places with the point of a knife. Then make a pickle with water and Vineger of equal quantity, with good ſtore of ſalt, wherein you ſhall put the Trout for the ſpace of almoſt halfe a day, then take it out and preſſe it two or thrée times on a Table for the ſpace of halfe an houre, then frie it very well in good oyle, but burne it not. In this ſort you may kéepe it for the ſpace of a month, and then frie it againe if you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Botarge, a kind of Italian meat.</head>
                  <p>Take the Spawnes of <hi>Cefano</hi> or <hi>Mugno</hi> that are freſh and in ſeaſon, and breake not the ſkin that is about them, and ſalt them with fine dry ſalt with diſcretion, &amp; ſo let them lie for a day and a night couered in Salt, then take them out and drie them in the ſmoke, but let them hang ſo far from the fire that the colour bee not hurt. And being thus dried for to kéep, you muſt put them in a wodden barrell filled with bran:
<pb facs="tcp:5822:28"/>
they are commonly eaten raw, but if you will haue them otherwiſe, you muſt roſt them in the embers, or vpon the whote hearth, turning them till they be whote.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Tonny.</head>
                  <p>Take Water and Vineger, and let the Tonny lie in it for two or thrée houres to take out the Salt, then ſet it to boyle ſoftly, which done, take it out and make it cleane, and ſouce it in vineger, the fatter it is, the better: &amp; the ſofter, the worſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Tonny another way, changing your water.</head>
                  <p>Lay it to ſoke in warme water twiſe or thriſe, then boile it two or thrée waumes, and being boiled take it vp and ſouce it in vineger, being well waſhed it may bee eaten raw, if a man will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a ſalt Eele.</head>
                  <p>Flay it &amp; cut it in péeces of a handfull long, and ſéeth it for the ſpace of halfe an houre, then caſt out that water, and put it in other cleane cold water, and let it boyle againe till it be wel boyled, ſo take it out &amp; eat it with Vineger and Parſely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe a Trout and all freſhwater fiſh, that hath been ſalted.</head>
                  <p>Let them ſtand in warme water for the ſpace of foure or fiue houres as they are in quantity, the like muſt you doe with all other fiſh. And note that of all fiſhes the greateſt are beſt, as the Prouerbe ſaith, Old fiſh, yong fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tarts in Lent and firſt of Creuiſſes.</head>
                  <p>Take Creuiſſes and ſéeth them, then take out all their
<pb facs="tcp:5822:29"/>
meat and ſtampe it in a morter, and take good Almond milke ſtrained with Roſewater, and if you haue it not, take good peaſe broth, and ſtamp theſe things with a few ſmal Reaſons and Figges, adding a few more ſmall Reaſons, Parſely, Margerum, and Bettonie, firſt fried in oile, and ſtirred with a knife, then put to it Ginger, Sinamon, and Sugar. This compoſition would bee ſtamped in a morter, and to make it thicken like milke, put a little flower into it, ſtirring them together, or the Spawnes of a Pike ſtamped and ſtrayned, which bind, and make a cruſt like other Tarts, and being baked, ſtraw it with Sugar and Roſewater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tarts of Eeles.</head>
                  <p>Flay the Eeles, and cut them in péeces of two fingers long, and ſéeth them, but not too much, then make Almond milke very white and faire, and ſtraine it with Veriuice and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and let the milke bee thicke, and ſtampe alſo a few Currans and dry Figges, then take Spinage broken in pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and fry it in oile, with a little parſely, broken and beaten ſmall, and an ounce of ſmall Reaſons, an ounce of the Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of Pine Apples, with Ginger, Sinamon, Pepper, and a little Saffron, according to the quantity you wil make, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and mixe all this compoſition well together. Then put the cruſt into a frying pan, and in it put your compoſition and then the Eeles, and ſo couer them againe with the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion till all the ſtuffe bee waſted, then couer it with paſte and bake it leiſurely with fire both ouer and vnder it, and when it is halfe baked take a little Veriuice, Roſewater, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and pricking holes in the lid put it into the Tart, and ſo let it ſtand vntill it be baked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tartes of Dates, Almonds, and other things.</head>
                  <p>Take two pounds of blanched Almonds, and ſtamp them
<pb facs="tcp:5822:29"/>
with fiſh broth and a little Roſe water, then ſtraine it and let it be ſomwhat thick, then take halfe a pound of clean Dates, a fewe Currans, and dried Figges, and beat all in a morter, then take a little Spinage, Parſely and Margerum, and frie them all in oyle &amp; ſtir it with a knife, adding to theſe hearbs certaine fat liuers and good fiſh beaten therewith, then take two ounces of the kernels of Pine apples very cleane, which you ſhall kéepe to ſtraw and ſticke vpon the Tart when it is made, and put it in the cruſt, then take Reaſons of the ſunne, and a pound of Sugar, Sinamon, Ginger, and a little Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and mingling all this together, you muſt temper it with one ounce of fine flower and a few Spawnes of a Pike, and mixe it with the other compoſition aforeſaid, and make the cruſt or paſte as aforeſaid, and ſo let it bake at leiſure, ſtraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sugar and Roſewater vpon it, you muſt not make it too thicke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Tart of Rice.</head>
                  <p>Take two pounds of blanched Almonds well ſtamped with a little Roſewater and Rice broth when it is almoſt ſodden, and temper Almonds therewith and ſtraine it, then take a pound of Rice and beate and temper it well with the Almonds, then put to it two ounces of white leauened dow, a little flower or elſe a few Spawnes of a Pike, and ſtraine it as aforeſaid with a pound of Sugar, and an ounce of the kernels of Pine apples broken in a morter but not ſtamped, and when it is halfe baked put a fine thin couer or lid vpon it, and being full baked, ſtraw it with Sugar and Roſewater, but let it not be too drie baked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Tart of red garden peaſe.</head>
                  <p>Séeth red Garden Peaſe, and being ſodden, ſtampe them and temper them with their broth and a little Roſewater, then ſtraine them, and take blanched Almonds according to the quantity you will make, and ſtampe them, but they muſt
<pb facs="tcp:5822:30"/>
not bee ſtrained, and with them ſtampe thrée ounces of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans and ſome dry Figges, and two ounces of Pine kernels not too much beaten, adding thereunto Sugar, Roſewater, Sinamon and Ginger, mingle all this together and thicken it with flower and the ſpawne of a Pike, and ſo bake him with a cruſt, and when it is almoſt baked, ſtraw it with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Roſewater, and let it drie vpon it. This Tart would not be thicke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Tart of the liuer of fiſhes, and of the fiſh it ſelfe.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the fiſh with the Liuers, then take ſodden Peaſe and ſtamp and ſtrain them, and likewiſe ſtampe the fiſh, and the liuers, taking out all the bones, and if you can get the Spawne of a Trout or Tench, it will bée good to ſtamp with them, then take Parſely and Margerum, and choppe it very ſmall, and ſtampe it in a morter with Sugar, Sinamon and Ginger as much as ſufficeth, mingle all theſe together with Roſewater, and let it bake ſoftly, &amp; when it is baked, obſerue the order aforeſaid. You may make all theſe kind of Tarts of diuers colours and ſeuerall meates in one pan as time ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, deuiding them into quarters, or otherwiſe as you think good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Marchpanes.</head>
                  <p>Blanch thy Almonds and ſtampe them very ſmall, but ſtraine them not, and to make the Almonds whiter, of better taſt, and ſwéeter, you muſt lay them for the ſpace of a day and a night in faire water, that they may blanch of themſelues betwéene your fingers, and ſtamping them you ſhall put in Roſewater that they bee not oiley, and if you make a very good Marchpane, put as much fine Sugar in it as there are Almonds in equall weight, with an ounce or two of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temper them together, then take Wafers or dow mixed with ſugar and temper it with Roſewater, then knead
<pb facs="tcp:5822:30"/>
it and lay the compoſition vpon it, &amp; in ſpreading it on ſprinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle it with Roſewater, then ſtraw it with fine Sugar ſmall beaten, and diſperce it with a ſpoone, ſo bake him in an ouen very ſoftly, and let it not burne neither bee ouerdrie, and it would not be thicke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make an Italian meat called <hi>Caliſcioni.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take Marchpane ſtuffe or ſuch as is ſpoken of in other places, prepare the paſte, Sugar, and Roſewater, then fill it with the ſtuffe, and if you haue a mould print it therewith to make it the fairer, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bake it in a pan or ouen like a March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane, but burne it not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Curds of Almonds in Lent.</head>
                  <p>Take blanched Almonds and ſtampe them with Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then with two ounces of Sugar, ten ounces of Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and halfe a pint of Pike or Tench broth, (for the broth of other ſea or freſh water fiſh is not good, and let not the broth be very ſalt but ſomewhat thicke) temper them together, and ſtraine it ſo hard that there remaine no part of the ſubſtance of the Almonds in the ſtrayner, let this Curd ſtand for the ſpace of one night, and put it in a diſh or other veſſell, and in the morning you ſhall find it curdy like curds of Milke. And if you will you may put them into gréene leaues or other hearbes like Chéeſe curds, or let it ſtand in the diſh, ſtrawing it with Sugar or Annyſéed Comfigs, you may adde thereto a little flower becauſe it bindeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To counterfet Lenten Cheeſe Curds.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of blanched Almonds and ſtampe them as aforeſaid, then take four ounces of Sugar, an ounce of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and a glaſſe full of fiſh broth as aforeſaid, and of the ſame fiſhes broth: then temper them together &amp; ſtrain them
<pb facs="tcp:5822:31"/>
thicke, then forme them and ſend them to the Table in a diſh or vpon a plate, ſtrawing it with Sugar and Annyſeed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To counterfeit Butter.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of blanched Almonds as aforeſaid, &amp; ſtamp them and ſtraine them with halfe a glaſſe of Roſewater, and to make them curdy put a little flower or half a glaſſe of Pike or Tench broth, with four ounces of Sugar and a little Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron to make it yellow, ſtraining it thick, then make it in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of a diſh of butter, and ſet it all night to thicken againſt morning in a cold place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To counterfeit Egges.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds and blanch them well and ſtampe them, tempering them with Roſewater that they bee not oiley, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome Pike broth that is fat, and ſtrain them like milke, then take halfe a pound of clean Rice according to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity you will make, which ſéeth in halfe the milke made of the Almonds: take alſo thrée ounces of the beſt &amp; whiteſt flower that may bee gotten, and diſſolue it in the other halfe of the milke, then let it boyle for the ſpace of halfe a quarter of an houre, ſtirring it with a ſpoon, and let it not taſt of the ſmoke: this done, take the Rice aforeſaid and all the milk, and ſtrain it hard with your hand, for the thicker the better, and forget not to adde good ſtore of Sugar, then take a quantity or part of the ſaid compoſition as much as you think good, which you ſhall make yellow with Saffron, and thereof make round Bals like the yolks of Egges, then take two wooden moulds in forme of Egges, and if you haue no moulds in ſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of take the made yolkes of Egges, compaſſing them about with the white compoſition, making them round like egges, and ſo lay them in the diſh, and they will ſhew like hard Egs without ſhels, &amp; tempering a little of that white ſtuffe with Roſewater and Sugar, whote or cold as you think good, they
<pb facs="tcp:5822:31"/>
will ſhew like curds. And if you will vſe them dry caſt none of that liquor vpon them, but in ſtead thereof caſt Sugar bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſmall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tartes of Cheſtnuts.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the Cheſtnuts and ſtampe and ſtraine them with milke, adding all the other compoſitions for the Tarts afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and make it yellow with Saffron.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tarts in fleſh time, and firſt to make a white Tarte.</head>
                  <p>Take two pounds of good new Chéefe and cut it ſmal, and then ſtampe it, then take fiftéene or ſixtéene whites of egges, and temper and mixe them with the Chéefe, putting thereto a pound of Sugar, halfe a pound of faire white Ginger, halfe a pound of ſwéet Butter, and ſome milke as much as wil ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, then make your paſte and let it be ſomewhat thin, and let it bake with a ſoft fire both vnder and ouer it, and let him bee ſomewhat browne, and when hee is baked ſtraw Sugar and Roſewater vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a greene Tarte after the manner of Bolognia.</head>
                  <p>Take as much Chéefe as aforeſaid, and grate it ſomwhat great, then take Parſely, Margerum, and other good hearbes chopped very ſmall and mixe them with the Chéeſe, &amp; ſtamp them in a morter adding thereto Egges, Pepper, and a little Saffron with ſwéet butter, then make a cruſt for it and bake it. And when it is halfe baked, colour it ouer with the yolke of an Egge and a little Saffron, and when the vpper cruſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it is baked, then take him from the fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:32"/>
                  <head>To make a Herboletta of hearbes in the month of May.</head>
                  <p>Take as much new chéefe as aforeſaid and ſtampe it, then take fiftéene or ſixtéene Egges and ſome milke, good ſtore of Bettonie, Margerum, Sage, Mint, and a little Parſely, ſtampe theſe hearbes very well and wring out the iuice and ſtraining it, you muſt put it into the Chéefe and other things aforeſaid, with halfe a pound of Butter, halfe a pound of Ginger, and ten ounces of Sugar, and mixe all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſet them on the fire in a pipkin not ouerwhote, and ſtirre it with a ſpoone vntill it begin to thicken like pottage: that done, hauing made paſte you ſhall put the compoſition into it, and ſet it to bake in a pan with a ſoft fire, both vnder and ouer it. And when it is well baked, take it out and ſtraw fine Sugar and Roſewater vpon it. This kinde of Tarte is beſt when it is gréeneſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tart of Pompeons.</head>
                  <p>Take Pompeons and make them cleane and grafe them as you doe Chéeſe, and boile them a little in broth or in milk, then take as much new Chéeſe as aforeſaid, adde to it alſo a little old Chéeſe, take alſo a pound of the panch of a Hogge, or a Cowes Vdder well ſodden and chopped ſmall, and if you will you may vſe Butter inſtead of thoſe two thinges afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or Suet, adding vnto it halfe a pound of Sugar, a little Saffron and Sinamon with a quart of milk, and Egges, as néed requireth. And when you thinke the Pompeons are ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den take them vp and ſtraine them, and colour it with a little Saffron, then making a cruſt of paſt vnder it, put it in a pan, and make a ſoft fire both vnder and ouer it, and being halfe baked, couer it with Wafers or ſuch like ſtuffe inſtead of an vpper cruſt, and being thorow baked, ſtraw it with Sugar and Roſewater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:32"/>
                  <head>To make Tartes of Peares, Turneps, and Quinces.</head>
                  <p>You may alſo as time ſerueth, make Tartes of Turneps and Peares, firſt roſting them in the embers, or with broken or ſwéet wine, ſo you may doe with Quinces, cutting them in quarters or péeces, making them clean, and boiling them: &amp; if you will you may roſt them in the embers, for ſo they wil be better, then ſtraine them, and adde ſuch things to them as are aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a kind of meat called <hi>Migliacio.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If you will make <hi>Migliacio,</hi> for foure or fiue perſons, you ſhall ſtampe two pounds of new Chéeſe ſo new as in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it ſhall be ready to turne to milke againe, then take foure ounces of fine flower, eight or ten whites of Egs, and halfe a pound of Sugar, mingling all this together, and if you haue not floure take crummes of white Bread grated very ſmall, and vſe it inſtead of flower, and take a pan without paſt, and put Butter into it about two fingers thicke, and let it ſtand on the coales vntill the Butter be melted, then put the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition into it with a reaſonable fire both vnder and ouer it, and when it is baked take it out and ſtraw Sugar and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tartes of Elder flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take the floures without kernels, and waſh them cleane with ſome of their branches, mixe them with the ſubſtance ſpoken of before for a white Tarte, but it would bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thicker becauſe the flowers would bee well ſeperated, whereby they may lie both aboue and below, and in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Tart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:33"/>
                  <head>To make Tartes of the ſmall greene thrids that wind about vine branches.</head>
                  <p>Take theſe Thrids about the vines and boile and choppe them with a knife, and the like may bee done with the red, then take good new Chéeſe and a Cowes vdder well ſodden, and ſtamp them together, and if you will in ſtead of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cowes Vdder you may vſe Suet or Butter, adding thereto Ginger, Sinamon, and a good quantity of Sugar, put this into a fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or baking pan, with paſte both vnder and aboue, &amp; when it is almoſt baked, pricke the vpper cruſt full of holes: being baked, ſtraw Sugar and Roſewater vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tartes of red Cherries.</head>
                  <p>Take the reddeſt Cherries that may bee gotten, take out the ſtones and ſtampe them in a morter, then take red Roſes chopped with a knife with a little new Chéeſe and ſome old Chéeſe well ſtamped with Sinamon, Ginger, Pepper, and Sugar, and all this mixed together, adde therevnto ſome egs according to the quantity you will make, and with a cruſt of paſte bake it in a pan, and being baked ſtraw it with Sugar and Roſewater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a fat Tarte with Rice.</head>
                  <p>Waſh the Rice well and make it cleane and boyle it in fat broth, and being boyled, take it out and dry it, then take a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle new Chéeſe ſtamped with Egges, Sugar, and Roſewater according to the quantity you will make, and if you will you may adde a little milke, and this being mixed together bake it in a pan, and obſerue the order preſcribed for white Tarts, but it muſt haue leſſe Chéeſe then the other aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:33"/>
                  <head>To make a Tarte of Wheat floure.</head>
                  <p>Make cleane the wheat and ſéeth it in fat broth, then take it out as you did the Rice, and take a pound of new Chéeſe, and halfe a pound of old Chéeſe grated and ſtamped together with a Cowes Vdder or Swines Panch, ſodden almoſt to Suet and minced with a knife, with Spice, Sugar, and egs, according vnto the quantity you wil make, with a little Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, mingle all this together, and then make an vnder cruſt of paſte and bake it, and when he is almoſt baked, couer him with the like couer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you vſe for the Pompeons or Gourds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Tarte of meale.</head>
                  <p>Take ſtamped meale very white and cleane, and ſéeth it in Goats milke or Cowes milke, and ſéeth it thick, then take a little fine floure and the whites of two Egges according to the quantity you wil make, and temper them with the meale ſtirring it with a ſpoon, then let it boile a little more, putting in Sugar and ſtirring it, and when this compoſition is made ſpread it vpon a trencher or other thing, and let it coole, and when you thinke good cut it in ſmall or great péeces as you will, then fry them in a pan with Butter, turning them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they bee browne, and then diſh them, and put Sugar and Roſewater vpon them. The like you may do in Lent by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Almond milke in ſtead of other milke, and frie them in oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Tarte of Veale, Kid, or Capon.</head>
                  <p>Take which of theſe meates you will both leane and fat, and boyle them, taking out all the ſinewes, then mince it and ſtampe it in a morter, then take a little new and old Chéeſe, Parſely, and Margerum, chopping them ſmall, and twelue or fiftéene Egs, with a Cowes Vdder wel ſodden, or a Hogs
<pb facs="tcp:5822:34"/>
panch well ſtamped, with Pepper, Saffron, Sinamon and Ginger, and bake it like other Tartes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a common Tarte.</head>
                  <p>Take good Chéeſe, Egs, Butter, Currans, Ginger, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon and Pepper, with a litle grated bread, with fat broth, coloured with Saffron, then vſe it as other Tarts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Tartes or Pies with broth.</head>
                  <p>Make a thicke cruſt of what bigneſſe you will, then take Pullets and Pigeons parboyled, cut them in quarters, and ech quarter into two or thrée péeces, then take blanched Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds ſtamped, yolkes of Egges, Saffron, fat broth, and a little Veriuice, and dry that cruſt or paſte like vnto other Pies, and make the ſides high, then fill it full of floure and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it with a lid, and let it bake till it bee ſtiffe, then cut open the lid and take out the flower, and then fill the Pie with the broth and meat aforeſaid, let it faſt well of Ginger and Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and bake it in an ouen like other Pies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Gealies of fleſh or fiſh, and of diuers colours in one platter.</head>
                  <p>If you will haue white Gealy, take good white Vineger or old Veriuice, and twice as much water, then take Shéeps féet or Kids féet flaien and made very cleane, eſpecially about the houſes, and cut them and take out the hairs in the middle, and waſh them well in cold water, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boyle them in the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Vineger and water, boyling them as ſoftly as you can, and with it boyle Ginger cut into ſmall péeces, &amp; whole graines of Paradiſe, and when the féet are indifferently boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led take them vp, and let the broth ſéeth a little when they are out: then take the whites of ten Egges more or leſſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quantity you will make, obſeruing the order in
<pb facs="tcp:5822:34"/>
ſtraining, clearing, and doing all other thinges elſe, which I will hereafter ſet downe in Gealy made of fleſh: and make ready the diſhes with Capons, Pullets, or other things vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which you will put this Gealie, and lay it finely on them, ſetting the diſhes in a cold freſh place becauſe it may thicken the better, then take out a good péece or a quarter of that gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the pot and ſet it on the fire in a pipkin vntill it be well melted, and that you ſée it returne to the forme againe, then take a little Saffron and make it yellow: and when it is cold, take of the foreſaid broth or ſome other thing made for the purpoſe, but let it not be whote when you put it in again, this being well ordered and hardened, take out another péece, and make it red with Carnels as I ſaied of Saffron, and ſo take out another péece to make gréen with wheat, or barly blades when they are yoong, and Parſely well ſtamped and ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and vſe it as the other two colours. Alſo you may make a ſanguine colour with Carriots roſted in the embers, and being roſted, make cleane the outſide with a knife which is ſanguine, and put in the bottome of the bag or ſtrainer, out of the which the compound or decoction is ſtrained, and as often as you receiue it out, you ſhall put it vpon the white broth well heated, obſeruing the like order in all the other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours aforeſaid, and place it in order with the other colours, you may make more colours if you will in the ſame manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Gealie of Creuiſſes which ſhall ſeeme aliue.</head>
                  <p>Take Creuiſſes in their ſhels, and lay them to ſoke in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, then take of the ſubſtance aforeſaid, and put it to them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make another faire Gealie.</head>
                  <p>Take forty Shéepes féet, and flea them, and take out the bones and haire, then lay them to ſoke in freſh water for the ſpace of thrée or foure houres, then waſh them, and then take
<pb facs="tcp:5822:35"/>
ſomewhat more then a quart of Vineger, as much White wine, and twice as much water, and ſéeth the féete therein, with ſalt to it as much as is conuenient, and ſkim them wel, and when they are halfe boyled, take a quarter of a pound of whole Pepper, as much long Pepper, and the like quantity of graines of Paradiſe, with a quarter of a pound of whole Sinamon, halfe a quarter of a pound of Spiknard &amp; Cloues, beat them all very groſſely all together, but not too much, and boyle them with the féet, and let them boyle till they bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to a third part, and when the féet are well boyled, take them out and let the broth ſéeth on the fire, and putting into it the whites of tenne Egges beaten together till they turne to a froth, and ſtirre it in the broth with a ſpoon, and then let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it boyle one waume, ſtraine it twice or thrice through a wollen cloth with all the compoſition: let it be well ſtrayned, and let the mixture remaine in the cloth, and the oftener it is ſtrained the better and clearer it is: then prepare your fleſh of Pullets, Capon, Rid, or Veale very well ſodden, pulling off the ſkins that it may bee faire and white, and ſo dry it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene two linnen clothes, then diſh it and lay the Gealie vpon it, and ſet them in a cold place that it may harden and congeale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Gealy of fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Take Water, Wine, and Vineger, and that it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long, take but a little water, and good ſtore of Spice as aforeſaid, the beſt fiſh for this purpoſe is Tench and Pike, and the greater the better, theſe fiſhes ſhould be opened but not ſcraped, very freſh, and ſodden in a little broth, onely as much as will couer them becauſe the broth may be the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and when you thinke the fiſh is well ſodden, take it out and flay it and then lay it aſide, but ſéeth the ſkinne a little in the broth, and when it is well ſod ſtraine it, obſeruing the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der aforeſaid in Gealie of fleſh, aſwell in making it yellow as in all other thinges. And you may in like ſort put any ſea fiſh ſodden and cut in quarters into this Gealie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:35"/>
                  <head>To make Gealie in a little basket.</head>
                  <p>Prepare the decoction in good order, then take a new baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and put the Capon, Pullet, or other fleſh into it, that you would put in Gealie as in a platter, you muſt likewiſe haue another veſſell ready wherein you may put the baſket, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the foreſaid decoction vpon it, and ſet it in a cold place to congeale, and when it is well congealed take a whote knife, and raiſe the Gealie round about within the baſket that it may eaſily come out, and make cleane the veſſel with a cloth in euery place, and ſo you may carry this Gealy whether you will. The like you may do in Lent, putting whole fiſh into it, which ſhall ſéeme aliue, and it will be very faire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Fritters of Cheeſe, Egges, and Elder flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take new and a little old Chéeſe and ſtampe them well, putting to it a little fine flower, and White of Egges accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quantity you will make, with a little Milke and good ſtore of Sugar, ſtamp them all together, then take it out of the morter, and put Elder flowers as your diſcretion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, neither beaten nor ſtamped. This compoſition would not bee too ſoft nor liquid, that it may bee wrought with the hand in any forme you will, then frie them in good Suet, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or Oyle, and ſend them whote to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Fritters of the white of Egges, and of flower and Cheeſe.</head>
                  <p>Obſerue the order aforeſaid, only not putting therto milk nor Elder flowers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:36"/>
                  <head>To make fritters of Creame and Curds.</head>
                  <p>Take the Curds and hauing cut them, ſtraine out the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or whay, and that which remaineth in the ſtrainer min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it with fine flower, white of Egges, Sugar and Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, according to the quantity you will make, it would not be too much congealed, &amp; make them great or little with a ſpoone as you thinke good, and frie them in ſuet or good Butter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of Sage and Bay-leaues.</head>
                  <p>Take a little fine flower and temper it with Egges, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Sinamon, Pepper, and a little Saffron to make it yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and take whole ſage leaues and roule them in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition one by one, and frie them in Butter or Suet. Do the like with Bayleaues, and in Lent frie them in oyle without Egges and Suet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of Apples.</head>
                  <p>Part them and ſéeth them, or roſt them, and take out the coates and ſtampe them, putting to them a little fine flower and a little leauen and frie them in good Oyle, you may cut them alſo into ſmall péeces, and take out the coare, and make the compoſition aforeſaid in the laſt chapter of Sage &amp; Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of Almonds, with the brawne or fleſh of a Henne.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds and ſtampe them with Roſewater and a little milke and ſtraine them, then take the brawne or fleſh of the breſt of a Pullet, boyle it and ſtampe it apart from the Almonds, then take a little flower and whites of Egges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quantity you will make, and a little Sugar, mingle all this together, and make your fritters in what
<pb facs="tcp:5822:36"/>
quantity you will, and frie them in Suet or Butter, and ſet them not be ouermuch baked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To frie Cheeſe in a pan.</head>
                  <p>Take Chéeſe which is not too old nor too ſalt, and cut it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſmall ſquare péeces or in what ſort you will, &amp; take a pan, in the bottome whereof put ſome Butter or Suet, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ouer the fire, put the ſaid péeces of Chéeſe into it, and when it is ſoft, turne it, and caſt Sugar and Sinamon vpon it and ſend it preſently to the Table: it is to bee eaten whote after meate. You may dreſſe it another way, that is, make toſts of bread, and when they are toſted lay them in the pan, and on euery toſt a péece of Chéeſe of the ſame greatneſſe, but ſomewhat thinner, then couer the pan and heat it vntill the Chéeſe curd, then caſt Sugar, Sinamon and Ginger vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Pancakes in Lent, and firſt of Elder floures.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds and ſtampe them, or elſe Pine apple ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, and ſtraine them with Roſewater and Peaſe broth, then take a little leauen, floures of Elders, and ſome flower, and temper them together, and this would bee made ouer night againſt morning, and ſo they will be the lighter: in the morning put good ſtore of Sugar on them, and make them in in what forme you will, and fry them in Oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of bitter hearbes.</head>
                  <p>Take fine flower and a little leauen, and temper it with the hearbes chopped ſmal, and Currans, and then frie them, this compoſition would not be too tender, fry the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Oyle, and caſt Sugar and Honny on them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:37"/>
                  <head>To make fritters of Rice.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the Rice well, and when it is ſed drie it vpon a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and if you will not haue it whole you may ſtamp it, then take Almonds and ſtampe and ſtraine them, with a little of the ſame Rice broth, and let this Almond milk be very thick, then take a little fine flower and Sugar, and mingling it all together, frie them in good Oyle in what faſhion you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of Figges.</head>
                  <p>Take a few Almonds and pine kernels, as many as you will and ſtampe them, let them bee very white, adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto two drie Figges and Currans with Spice, and if this ſtuffe be too thick put a little Roſe water to it, then take Figs and make a hole in ech Figge hard by the ſtalke, and fil them with this ſtuffe, then frie them in oyle and caſt Sugar on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of Fiſh.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the fiſh and ſtampe the whiteſt part thereof, then take Almonds well ſtamped and ſtrained, and a little fine floure with Sugar and Sinamon, and temper all this with a little common water, then frie it in oyle in what forme you will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters like fiſhes.</head>
                  <p>Blanch thy Almonds and take meat of fiſh without bones and ſtampe them together with Currans, Sugar, Parſely and Margerum chopped ſmall with good Spice and Saffron, then haue in a readineſſe a fine paſte, and making it in what forme you wil you may fill them with this compoſition, then frie them in oile: they make likewiſe be baked dry in a frying pan, and when they are baked, they will ſhew like fiſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:37"/>
                  <head>To make them another way.</head>
                  <p>Stampe Almonds and temper them with Roſewater and Sugar, then take flower tempered with common water and good ſtore of Sugar, this being made in paſt, make what form of fiſh you will deuiſe: alſo you may bake them dry in a pan like a Tarte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters in another ſort.</head>
                  <p>You ſhall make a compoſition like the aforeſaid Almonds, flower, and Sugar, and thereof make thy fritters.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make another ſort.</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds blanched, Pine kernels, or Nuts, or any of them, ſtampe them wel with Currans or Figges, putting to them the meat or liuers of fiſhes, with Parſely, Marge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, and good Spices, and make it yellow with Saffron, then forme them and frie them with oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters of Rice like little Pies.</head>
                  <p>Séeth the Rice and ſtamp your Almonds and ſtrain them as thicke as you can, with a little Roſewater, and mixe the Rice well with the Almonds, and with Sugar, Sinamon, and a little flower, and make it in forme of Pies and fry them in oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fritters full of wind, or puſt fritters.</head>
                  <p>Take fine flower, water, Salt, and Sugar, and make a fine ſoft paſt and roule it on a Table very thinne, and cut it into ſmall péeces and frie it in oyle, and take heed they be not knotty, and they will puffe vp and ſéeme to bee full, and yet
<pb facs="tcp:5822:38"/>
there is nothing in them, and caſt Honny vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make them in another manner.</head>
                  <p>Make your paſte like that I ſpake of before, to make frit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of curds and Creame, then take Fennell when it is blowne, and if you will, mixe it and all the ſtuffe together: or breake euery branch by it ſelfe one by one, and roule them in the ſaid ſtuffe, and frie them in oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To frie <hi>Piſtinachie</hi> Nuts.</head>
                  <p>Make them very clean and take out the hard matter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, then ſéeth them, and when they are ſod roule them in flower, and frie them in oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Egges all manner of waies, and firſt to make a Pancake.</head>
                  <p>Firſt you ſhall beat the Egs together with a little milke and water to make them tender, and a little grated Chéeſe, and then frie them in good Butter that they may bee the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; to make them good, they would not be turned nor much baked, and ſo ſend it to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a greene Pancake.</head>
                  <p>Take the things aforeſaid, and adde thereto the iuice of Bettonie, Parſely, good ſtore of burrage, Mints, Margerum, Sage a little, and ſtraine this iuice through a cloth, and ſo make the Pancake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make another Pancake of hearbes.</head>
                  <p>Take the foreſaid hearbes, and cutting them ſmall, frie them in Butter or Oyle, mingling them with Egges and
<pb facs="tcp:5822:38"/>
other thinges aforeſaid, then make the Pancake and frie it well, and let it be thicke but not ouerbaked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe Egges another way.</head>
                  <p>Put oyle in the pan, and breake new laid Egges in it, and frie them ſoftly, and as they frie ſtirre them, and when they congeale and waxe thicke and white, they are fried, but frie them not too drie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To poche Egges.</head>
                  <p>Let the water be whote, and breake new laied Egges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and when they are thicke, take them out becauſe they may be tender, then put Sugar, Roſewater, and a little iuice of Orenges or Veriuice on them, or if you will, throw gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chéeſe and ſpice vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To poche them in milke or wine.</head>
                  <p>Doe as aforeſaid, onely that you ſhall ſtraw no Chéeſe on them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To dreſſe and fill Egges.</head>
                  <p>Séeth new Egs in water vntill they be hard, then péele them and cut them in the middle, and take out the yolks, and doe not breake the white, and ſtamp ſome part of thoſe yolks with a few Currans, Parſely, Margerum and Mint, chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped very ſmall, with two or thrée whites of Egs, with what ſpice you thinke good. And when they are mixed together co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour it with Saffron, and fill the Egges therewith, and frie them in oyle: and for ſauce take a fewe of thoſe yolkes which remaine vnſtamped with a few Currans, and ſtampe them well together, and temper them with a little Veriuice, and ſtraine them, putting thereto Sugar, Cloues, and good ſtore of Sinamon, let this ſauce boyle a little, and when you will ſend the Egges to the Table, put this ſauce vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>To roſt Egges vpon a gredyron.</head>
                  <p>Beat two or thrée new laied Egges together, and heat an empty frying pan very well, and put theſe beaten Egges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and let them ſpread about the frying pan as thinne as paper, and when they are baked, cut them in foure péeces and lay them on the gredyron, and breake ouer them as many new Egges as will lie vpon them, and make a ſoft fire both vnder and ouer them like a Tart, and ſtraw them with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Sinamon, and when the Egges are thick, take them off the gredyron in that maner, and ſend them to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt Egges on a ſpit.</head>
                  <p>Heat your ſpit very whote, and tie the Egges longwaies or otherwiſe vpon it, and roſt them like meat, and when they are roſted take out the meat and ſend them to the Table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To frie Egges.</head>
                  <p>Put good Butter in the Pan and heat it a little, then take the yolkes of Egges and frie them, with Sugar and Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and make a moderate fire as to a Tarte, then put the iuice of Orenges or Roſewater vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt them in whote embers.</head>
                  <p>Put them into the whote embers, turning them oft on euery ſide, and when they ſweat they are roſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth Egges with the ſhell.</head>
                  <p>Put them in cold water, and make it boyle a Pater noſter while, and then take them out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:39"/>
                  <head>To dreſſ them after the manner of Florence.</head>
                  <p>Take new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ied Egges, and breake them one by one in a pan, and let the oyle be very whote, and as ſoone as you haue put them into the oyle, ſtirre them together with a ſpoone or ſome other thing, and make them as round as may bee, and turne them oft vntill they change colour, and yet let them not be hard within, nor ouerbaked, but rather ſoft &amp; tender.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another kind of dreſsing them.</head>
                  <p>Take whole Egges and lay them into the embers, then ſtrike them with a ſmall ſticke vntill they breake, and ſo let them roſt, and when they are roſted, take them out and caſt a little Vineger and Parſely vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another way.</head>
                  <p>Dreſſe them in the Florentine manner as aforeſaid, then ſtraw Sugar, Spice, and Salt on them, and ſo put them into paſte as you would doe Turneps, and fry them or ſéeth them, you may dreſſe them alſo in pie paſte with the foreſaid ſtuffe, adding a little Veriuice, baking them like Tartes, or frying them, but let them not bee ouerbaked, becauſe they will bee the harder, and ſo much the worſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To prepare Hogges greaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take freſh larde or fat of a Hog, and cut it like to Cheſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts and ſalt it well, then ſtampe it well and let it ſtand for the ſpace of a day, then ſet it on the fire, and if it bee an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, put in it tenne or twelue quartes of water to it, and let it ſéeth vntill it be congealed, then ſkim it and ſtraine it, and put it into a veſſell in a freſh and cold place, and by this order it will continue a whole yeare or more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5822:40"/>
                  <head>To make wine of water.</head>
                  <p>Take the grapes of a wild vine and drie them in the ſon, then beat them into powder, and put them into water and it will haue the taſt and colour of wine, &amp; if the grape be white it will haue the ſame colour, if red the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſweet white Wine.</head>
                  <p>Take good ſwéet Apples according to the quantity of the Wine and ſtampe them well, and put halfe as much Honny as Apples, and mingle them together, then put it into the wine in the veſſell and mingle it well: and this is done beſt with new wine that boyleth in the Vate, or elſe boyle theſe things in ſome veſſell with ſome new wine, then put it to the other, and ſtirre them together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make meat for Nightingales.</head>
                  <p>Take a dramme of Almonds, two drams of Peaſe floure, a dramme of freſh Butter, two drammes of Honny, a little Saffron and two yolkes of Egges, mixe them together, and ſet them to the fire in a pipkin, &amp; giue it to the Nightingales.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a compoſition of Pompeons or Mellons.</head>
                  <p>The Pompeons or Mellons would bee ſcoured and made cleane in Vineger and not in water, and ſo ſtand a moneth or more in Vineger, and if néed be the vineger may be changed, and then put them in Honny like vnto a Gourd, and they are made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Compoſition of Figs, very cordiall.</head>
                  <p>Firſt prepare your Figs ready in a cleane veſſell, which
<pb facs="tcp:5822:40"/>
are to bee conſerued, then boyle the Honny and ſkim it well, and being whote put it on the Figges, and let them ſtand in it till it bee cold, this you ſhall doe foure or fiue times, the laſt time take new Honny and boyle it well, and put to it Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Sinamon and Cloues, then put the Figges in the pot wherein they ſhall remaine, being conſerued, theſe Spices muſt bee beaten ſmall, and ſet the Figges in a veſſell in the ſunne, and now and then put Honny mixed with the Spices aforeſaid, and ſo the Figges will be conſerued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſtrong Vineger and quickly.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of Pellitory well ſtamped and put it in four pottles of wine, then take the foreſaid Pellitory, and boyle it in foure or fiue quarts of ſtrong Vineger, and ſo boyling put it into the caſke, and in twelue daies it will be good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
